<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Andrew Paradi</title>
    <description>Growth Focused Front End Developer
</description>
    <link>//andrewparadi.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="//andrewparadi.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 01:00:05 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 01:00:05 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Favourite 6 Books Since June</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome my new (much faster) blog! I&amp;#39;ll have a post out soon about what&amp;#39;s new but it&amp;#39;s New Year&amp;#39;s Eve! Before 2015 is finished, I&amp;#39;d like to share some of my favourite books I&amp;#39;ve finished since June 2015!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking for favs before June? &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/leisure-reading-part-1/&quot;&gt;Check out this post.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Elon Musk - Ashlee Vance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-12-31-leisure-reading-part-2/elon-musk-ashlee-vance.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book was on my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/leisure-reading-part-1/&quot;&gt;currently reading list back in June&lt;/a&gt;. Two weeks after the post went up, I was finished. Everyone knows that Elon Musk is known for Tesla cars and SpaceX rockets but few know what he&amp;#39;s like as a person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after reading the book, I can&amp;#39;t say that I understand him as a person. Elon Musk is exceptionally complex. He is clearly intelligent. He has unbreakable determination, willing to bet his life savings on his companies at the peak of global economic chaos in December 2008. He is a passionate father of five sons yet still very &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marieclaire.com/sex-love/advice/a5380/millionaire-starter-wife/&quot;&gt;calculating&lt;/a&gt; in how much time and emotion he allocates to family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In interviews with co-founders, family, and employees, it became clear that labels or archetypes simply don&amp;#39;t grasp the complexity of the man. Elon isn&amp;#39;t diagnosed with anything on the autism spectrum. Though Musk inspired Robert Downey Jr,&amp;#39;s portrayal of Tony Stark in Iron Man, Musk doesn&amp;#39;t have the empathy of Stark. Musk even fired his long time secretary, Mary Beth Brown, unimaginable for the fictional Stark and his secretary Pepper Potts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-frc/t51.2885-15/e15/10731621_742514089151424_1105265047_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Test driving a Tesla Model S P85 in California. October 2014.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk is unique. Of all his accomplishments, his realistic perspective on clean energy economics is like a breath of fresh air in the &amp;quot;green&amp;quot; industry that primarily uses moral arguments to push their agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ted.com/talks/bill_gates&quot;&gt;Bill Gates&lt;/a&gt;, Musk believes that until solar or nuclear energy is cheaper than coal, there will be no mass migration away from fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Gates funds a diverse set of clean energy initiatives, Musk focuses on optimizing all aspects of the solar economics equation. Solar City has drastically improved per unit costs and user experience for solar panel installation. Tesla&amp;#39;s new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teslamotors.com/powerwall&quot;&gt;Powerwall&lt;/a&gt; makes it possible to store energy and live entirely off the grid. And of course, Tesla cars are completely emission free (and jaw-droppingly fun to drive).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eagerly look forward to the day I can live off the grid in a small solar powered house with a Tesla in the driveway. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book gives a deeper look into the man who will make this future a reality for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Emotional Intelligence 2.0 - Travis Bradberry &amp;amp; Jean Greaves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-12-31-leisure-reading-part-2/Emotional_Intelligence_2.0-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received this as a gift for my birthday in June and it certainly played as an ironic book to read after &lt;em&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#39;s a concisely written book with many examples for the four areas of personal competence (self-awareness and self-management) and social competence (social awareness and relationship management).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each category came with 15-20 strategies that, though many sounded completely intuitive (&amp;quot;Don&amp;#39;t be fooled by a bad mood&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Know who and what pushes your buttons&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Count to Ten&amp;quot;...), had me quickly thinking of ways I could be using them more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reading, I almost always found myself imagining times when I (or somebody I knew) had successfully used (or failed to use) the strategy. Unlike Myers-Briggs, DISC, and EQI assessment literature, Emotional Intelligence 2.0 gave me practical insights and was engaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at successful people across industries and times, the ability to read, manage, and manipulate emotions has built empires, won wars, and inspired generations of people. Learning these skills ourselves gives us a good foundation to be successful in our own life, and I&amp;#39;d recommend this book as a good place to start if you&amp;#39;re a rookie like me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Stephen Harper - John Ibbitson&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-12-31-leisure-reading-part-2/stephen_harper_john_ibbitson.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I confess. I follow politics. Mostly US politics (way more exciting) but this year was special. 2015 was a election year in Canada, and what a roller coaster it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite growing up with Stephen Harper as Prime Minister for most of my life, I didn&amp;#39;t know much about him. This book was a unique window into one of the most reclusive men to ever hold the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book works in chronological order through young Steve&amp;#39;s growing up in Toronto suburb, Leaside, health problems that made him more hockey fan than player, and a short lived university education at University of Toronto&amp;#39;s prestigious Trinity College. The Trinity College section was fascinating having read months before about Jim Balsille&amp;#39;s time there in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/leisure-reading-part-1/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Losing the Signal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elite Trinity College community that fostered RIM co-founder Jim Balsille&amp;#39;s competitive spirit, repelled Harper who dropped out within weeks of his freshman year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harper then escaped to Calgary where he transitioned from &amp;quot;Trudeau Liberal&amp;quot; to Reform conservative and from Steve to Stephen. Stephen Harper married, rose through the ranks of local riding associations, worked as assistant to MP&amp;#39;s in Ottawa, and eventually became leader of the Canadian Alliance Party which merged with the Progressive Conservatives in 2003 to become the Conservative Party that we know today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally felt that I understood better some of the unique attitudes of Canadians living in the Western provinces. The latter third of the book goes behind the scenes of the scandals and major decisions that defined the Harper years. What was most fascinating though was that so many of the peculiarities of Harper&amp;#39;s behaviour and leadership style come down to a single character flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen Harper will take orders from no one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stephen Harper&lt;/em&gt; is the book one would write if given the above thesis statement as an essay prompt. Harper&amp;#39;s life is consistently used to point back as proof to this thesis, and the proof is compelling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would Harper drop out of UofT when he was an incredibly successful student in high school? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would he consistently buck the traditional &amp;quot;House of Cards&amp;quot; ladder-climbing loyalty that dominated the logic of his political peers, and quit or alienate himself from nearly every position he ever held? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would he break every PR rule by publicly attacking Canadian Supreme Court Justices? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would he ignore and try to bury non-partisan government officials and their reports?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why, why, why...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this personality flaw that would have crippled most people to recurrent career failure and eventual humility, Harper&amp;#39;s journey is remarkable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charting a different path, Harper found a job where he would never have to take orders. And for almost 10 years, he never did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond just seeing behind the curtain of Canadian government, John Ibbitson&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;Stephen Harper&lt;/em&gt; shares an understanding of how Stephen Harper, the man, thought and made decisions. His legacy is a complex one and I&amp;#39;m glad I read this book to see another side to the man who was our 22nd Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Homeland - Cory Doctorow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-12-31-leisure-reading-part-2/homeland_cory_doctorow.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;This is the sequel to Doctorow&amp;#39;s award winning &lt;em&gt;Little Brother&lt;/em&gt; which I read &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/leisure-reading-part-1/&quot;&gt;earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;. Unlike most sequels, Homeland lived up to expectations.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s another thrilling ride through the near future that is increasingly descriptive of the present we live in today. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theintercept.com/&quot;&gt;Edward Snowden. The NSA. PRISM. Encryption wars. Mass data collection.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/2015/07/hackers-remotely-kill-jeep-highway/&quot;&gt;Cars being hacked&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology is no longer a tool for the people. It&amp;#39;s a tool for controlling the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully the future isn&amp;#39;t entirely here yet. &lt;a href=&quot;https://gnupg.org/download/index.html&quot;&gt;PGP email encryption.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://chatsecure.org/&quot;&gt;ChatSecure.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/tour&quot;&gt;DuckDuckGo.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/&quot;&gt;TOR.&lt;/a&gt; There are many tools available that can keep your emails private from ad targeting, your chats with friends private from subpoenas to Facebook or Kik, and remove your searches from Google&amp;#39;s records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes minutes to install these tools. But they are useless unless our friends and family use these tools too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please give them a try, send me your PGP fingerprints! Help your family and friends understand why privacy and encryption is important. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Help make our future one where privacy and freedom still exist. A future where we don&amp;#39;t need to fear prying eyes from corporations or governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may hear people say that we don&amp;#39;t need these tools if we don&amp;#39;t have anything to hide. Do you enjoy walking outside naked? Or having private conversations with loved ones read aloud on CNN? Me neither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy has been an essential part of the human experience. Hoping that it continues to be doesn&amp;#39;t make anybody a terrorist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://craphound.com/category/homeland/&quot;&gt;Download Homeland for free on Cory Doctorow&amp;#39;s site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Being Mortal&amp;#58; Medicine and What Matters in the End - Atul Gawande&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-12-31-leisure-reading-part-2/being-mortal-atul-gawande-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Nothing is certain except death and taxes&amp;quot; - Benjamin Franklin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And leading up to death, is aging. In the Western world, aging often culminates in stay in a nursing home with progressively greater levels of care from assisted living to complete hospital style nursing. The elderly are treated more like patients than people, have their independence stripped from them, and lose a sense of purpose for their life. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atul Gawande addresses the important question, &amp;quot;is there a better way?&amp;quot; with the perspective that only a surgeon can bring. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He works through the history of elderly care in the Western world, and how it works very differently everywhere else. While Western families move their elderly into nursing homes, most elderly in the rest of the world move in with their children&amp;#39;s families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple generations live under one roof. Grandchildren keep grandparents entertained and active. Grandparents pass wisdom on in day to day life, not just in hour long visits while they lay in a hospital bed. Nursing care happens in the family home where elderly can remain in a place they know with people they love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nursing homes are designed for medical care, for the families, for society. But rarely are they designed with their elderly in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being Mortal&lt;/em&gt; helped me realize that the vast majority of doctors don&amp;#39;t know when to say &amp;quot;enough is enough&amp;quot;. At some point, more medical treatment isn&amp;#39;t worth it when the extra weeks of life you might get aren&amp;#39;t a life worth living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Other Readings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-12-31-leisure-reading-part-2/you-and-me-forever-c.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also finished reading &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; by J.R.R. Tolkien and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youandmeforever.org/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;You and Me Forever&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Francis and Lisa. Francis is one of my favourite authors and his book on building a marriage with perspective of eternity is excellent. Francis and Lisa are donating all proceeds to their project in in East Africa to free sex slaves, empower women, and build lasting communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After recommendations from family and friends over multiple years, I&amp;#39;m finally reading &lt;em&gt;Good to Great&lt;/em&gt; by Jim Collins. Just a couple chapters in and I&amp;#39;m already starting to see why this book can change how you think about building an high performing organization that lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I may not be a Level 5 leader yet, but I sure hope to be someday. Until then, I&amp;#39;ll keep reading. I hope you will to.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 20:34:25 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/blog/leisure-reading-part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/blog/leisure-reading-part-2/</guid>
        
        <category>life</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Startups Fail Even with Cash and Growth</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everybody in startups should be reading Paul Graham&amp;#39;s essays. He just hit it out of the park again. Go read &lt;a href=&quot;http://paulgraham.com/aord.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Default Alive or Default Dead?&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; and then come back.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve co-founded a startup (&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-dream-fades/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;), worked as a growth intern at another (&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;), and met with hundreds of founders over the past two years. These classic 3 steps to success more often than not were the foundation for too many startups:
- Funding will finally let us hire, scale, grow, develop, succeed...
- Growth will get us funding
- Collect $100k - $100 million from VCs, Rinse, Repeat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m as guilty as any to have held this view. After reflecting on Teknically and working with other startups since, my eyes have been opened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham puts it so well in his latest post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Here&amp;#39;s a common way startups die. They make something moderately appealing and have decent initial growth. They raise their first round fairly easily because the founders seem smart and the idea sounds plausible. But because the product is only moderately appealing, growth is ok but not great. The founders convince themselves that hiring a bunch of people is the way to boost growth. Their investors agree. But (because the product is only moderately appealing) the growth never comes. Now they&amp;#39;re rapidly running out of runway. They hope further investment will save them. But because they have high expenses and slow growth, they&amp;#39;re now unappealing to investors. They&amp;#39;re unable to raise more, and the company dies.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m just speechless how clearly this explains the systematic failure inherent in the most common founder perspective on startup success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Founders are baited by initial VC money to optimize for quick launch and fast growth. This all to the peril of building a product and business model that will last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s easy to dismiss this and believe that your startup and perspective is different. Yet, too many founders are blind leading the blind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many startup cultures don&amp;#39;t encourage any employees to voice concerns or ask questions. Founders spin anything to reinforce their viewpoint that success will come with the next founding round or growth spurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish more founders would step back and realize if they&amp;#39;re default dead or default alive. I didn&amp;#39;t do this myself in Teknically and regret the ultimate cost of our &amp;quot;it&amp;#39;s going great&amp;quot; culture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking back, we were default dead. We just didn&amp;#39;t realize it until we had died.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 12:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/blog/how-startups-fail-even-with-cash-and-growth/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/blog/how-startups-fail-even-with-cash-and-growth/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Losocco</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Built at Hack the North 2015, Losocco is Amazon meets Craigslist for local stores. Customers can browse aggregated inventories of all local stores, see where items are closest to them on a map, pay with PayPal or Bitcoin, save their favourites with their Facebook Login, and local stores get seamless Quickbooks integration for all in app transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team of four built Losocco using Meteor.JS and many sponsor APIs as listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I designed and coded the custom Google Maps integration with their Javascript API, the new product form and merchant account page with HTML5/CSS3, and produced the demo video above in 36 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out a live demo at &lt;a href=&quot;http://losoc.co&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;losoc.co&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/a3-RnvmDsZ8?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 13:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/project/losocco/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/project/losocco/</guid>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>HTML/CSS</category>
        
        <category>paypal</category>
        
        <category>google-maps</category>
        
        <category>hack</category>
        
        <category>pitch</category>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Videostream: How Growth Starts with Great Customer Support</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As a Growth Intern at &lt;a href=&quot;http://getvideostream.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Videostream&lt;/a&gt;, I used my customer support job to hack growth on all fronts. After answering thousands of customer emails, I could write sales copy that resonated. Website downloads went up by 32%, weekly active users grew 12%, and revenue even went up! Find out how you can do it too.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Update Oct 22: Approval from legend &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/copyhackers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joanna&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://copyhackers.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Copyhackers&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;nice work! *really* great study on optimizing for growth in a short period of time &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/BZPdRb2Pbj&quot;&gt;https://t.co/BZPdRb2Pbj&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Joanna Wiebe (@copyhackers) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/copyhackers/status/657363804162949121&quot;&gt;October 23, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Customer Support Lead for 1.2 million user base&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As customer support lead for Videostream&amp;#39;s 1.2 million user base, I answered a lot of email every day. I was the first point of contact anytime a Videostream user had an issue, feature request, or even just wanted to share how much they loved our app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times it was overwhelming, occasionally humbling, and on a lucky day, I&amp;#39;d receive a genuinely hilarious email and try to craft my wittiest reply. For most emails though, I started to recognize patterns in both support and testimonials. For faster responses, I wrote almost 90 canned responses to cover countless problems and permutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Over 4 months, I ended up resolving 2,148 tickets for our customers and with my canned responses, I resolved them faster than ever.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/nice-message.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Videostream Support Email #781: One of the better emails I found waiting for me in Freshdesk one morning.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through reading positive feedback I started to understand why customers loved Videostream so much. As I wrote sales copy, I could reference customer testimonials and highlight the features that they were most excited about. Many loved the funny tips screens that had jokes and referenced that our team was just 6 guys in Canada. This confirmed that the Videostream personality that resonated with users should be part of all future sales copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;#39;t have written as effective sales copy if I hadn&amp;#39;t spent the time to understand our customers: their frustrations, their joys, and their dreams for Videostream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Building a Split Test Winning Website&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Videostream team had reached a consensus: the website was long due for a makeover and I would lead development on a full redesign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/vs-old-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Original Videostream Website&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started brainstorming what I the ideal new website would be like. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It would be easier to understand what was Videostream.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hero images would showcase how Videostream worked with laptops, TVs, iPhones and Android devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Descriptions would quickly address frequently emailed questions like: &amp;quot;will Videostream play my videos?&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first focused on the &amp;quot;above the fold&amp;quot; content, or what a visitor would see before they scrolled. As I bounced between different drafts for the subtitle, I realized that using a word substitution animation would allow us to subtly show just how many files we supported. With a simple Javascript animation, &amp;quot;The easiest way to stream ____ from your computer...&amp;quot; would animate the blank to say: videos, MP4s, MKVs, AVIs, MP3s... switching every 4 seconds. This instantly addressed above the fold the question: &amp;quot;will Videostream play my videos?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stay consistent with the app&amp;#39;s existing design style, I found a great Material Design HTML/CSS/JS framework to build on (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.materialup.com/posts/mdlp-material-design-landing-page&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;). I got to work on customizations and generating the Hero image assets in Photoshop. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leveraging my knowledge from leading sites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://copyhackers.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Copyhackers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://moz.com/blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moz&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.kissmetrics.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kissmetrics&lt;/a&gt;, I focused all visitors towards a single Call to Action (CTA) above the fold: the &amp;quot;Get Streaming&amp;quot; download button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/vs-home-c.png&quot; alt=&quot;New Site Hero: The view above the fold any visitor to GetVideostream.com will see. Notice the singular focus on quickly describing what is Videostream, and pushing visitors to download.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I continued writing sales copy, I focused on consistency with the Videostream personality customers already loved. For Features and FAQs, I leveraged all I had read in customer emails what they loved most about Videostream, and questions that kept coming up. I also maintained consistency repeating certain phrases in headings and text to better target certain keywords we wanted to take in Google rankings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/vs-features-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Features Section: Using customer testimonials, I could accurately prioritize which features people loved the most and which benefit resonated best.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few quick weeks of development, my new website was ready to go head to head with the old site. With consistently high web traffic, we could make a statistically significant call on which site was the winner in under a week. &lt;strong&gt;Pretty soon we could see a trend. The new website was seriously rocking the numbers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;65% of visitors to the new website downloaded Videostream, up from 54% on the old website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the new website, I put CTA download buttons after every section. Now we would know which content led people to download. Though most people downloaded just from the Hero section above the fold, close to 20% of downloads were coming from Features, Testimonials, and FAQ sections. Those downloads would have never happened on the old website which relied on a single CTA and a lot less content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After beating the old site in spilt tests, the new site was pushed to 100% of traffic. We were excited for the spike in downloads that would come for a higher conversion rate but were surprised what we saw when we logged into Google Analytics the following week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/weekly-active-users2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Videostream App Usage Data: Weekly active users with the old website, and the 12% jump from the new website.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were shocked when weekly active users shot up 12%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within a week of the new website launching, weekly active users in the app shot up 12%. They&amp;#39;ve since stayed high and been one of the biggest single growth jumps we had this summer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out many people were going to the main website to launch Videostream which meant that our huge boost came not only from new downloads, but from bringing existing users back more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My vision for a conversion focused website had worked! Download conversions were up on many metrics up to 32% and weekly active users had received a 12% boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next project...increasing revenue!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Premium Flow Focused on Revenue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My internship was almost done. I had answered a lot of email and developed a new split test beating website. The team now was curious to see what I could do with their primary revenue funnel: the Premium flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/premo1-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Premium Flow: Features &amp;amp; Plans.&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/premo2-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Premium Flow: Payment Confirmation.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current upgrade process was a bit convoluted. Most interactions such as changing a plan or choosing a payment required a separate page and a number of clicks. From customer emails, I knew that even with the features descriptions front and centre, most still had no idea what they would be getting with Premium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My priorities with the new Premium flow ended up being very similar to what I settled on for the website previously:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write sales copy based on customer feedback with the much loved Videostream personality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow Material Design guidelines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make Premium benefits easier to understand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let people buy Premium in fewer clicks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a lot of research from e-commerce checkout white papers to successful upgrade flows in other apps. I built the premium flow from scratch with HTML/CSS/Sass, Stripe API, PayPal integration, and Javascript. I&amp;#39;m so thankful to the team for all they taught me about coding for a Chrome App.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/premflow1-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Premium Flow: Plans, Payment Selection, &amp;amp; Features.&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/premflow2-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Premium Flow: Payment Confirmation.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Premium flow was almost in production as I finished my internship at Videostream. The benefits of Videostream were now easy to understand. Upgrading was fast and seamless and could be done in fewer clicks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Premium flow is in split tests now where it is rumoured to be winning and generating more revenue for Videostream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Growth? Check, check, and check&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Videostream, I leveraged my primary task of email support to better understand our customers and spur growth in different parts of our funnel. The new website increased download conversions by up to 32% on most metrics. We improved user retention with weekly active users growing by 12%. Revenue is now going up thanks to a more effective Premium flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I grew a lot. The experience of owning a project, working closely with founders, collaborating with a crazy good technical team, and supporting thousands of customers was priceless. I learned so much. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m thankful to Matt, Jason, Graham, Joe, Phillip, Sean, &amp;amp; Rahul for all of the support, guidance, and unique opportunities I received this summer. It&amp;#39;s certainly one I won&amp;#39;t soon forget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P.S. I&amp;#39;m looking to do an internship next summer too! If you think I&amp;#39;d be a good fit on your team, check out my &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/files/AndrewParadiResume.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;resume&lt;/a&gt; and send me an email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:me@andrewparadi.com&quot;&gt;me@andrewparadi.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 18:50:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/blog/videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/blog/videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Videostream</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As Summer &amp;#39;15 Growth Intern, I got to work on three awesome projects on one of the most popular video streaming apps for Chromecast.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lead customer support for &lt;a href=&quot;http://getvideostream.com/&quot;&gt;Videostream&amp;#39;s&lt;/a&gt; over 1.2 million customers. That meant resolving 2,148 email support tickets over 4 months and writing close to 90 canned responses so I could do my job more efficiently&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With in depth customer knowledge and feedback, I could confidently redesign the &lt;a href=&quot;http://getvideostream.com/&quot;&gt;Videostream website&lt;/a&gt; to focus on the benefits that resonated with customers. The new website I developed beat split tests across the board and on certain metrics had up to 32% better download conversion rates than the old website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-09-06-videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/premflow1-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Premium Flow: Plans, Payment Selection, &amp;amp; Features.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked on a new Premium flow in the app which makes upgrading to new features significantly easier for customers. I built the flow from scratch using HTML/Sass, Javascript, and integrations with Stripe, Paypal, and Google O-Auth APIs. It&amp;#39;s beating the original Premium flow in initial revenue split tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/videostream-how-growth-starts-with-great-customer-support/&quot;&gt;Read more about how I helped Videostream grow and see before and after screenshots here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 15:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/project/videostream/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/project/videostream/</guid>
        
        <category>material-design</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>HTML/Sass</category>
        
        <category>sales-copy</category>
        
        <category>paypal</category>
        
        <category>customer-support</category>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Frank&#39;s Jewellers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Frank&amp;#39;s Jewellers has been trusted by couples and jewellery shoppers in Uptown Waterloo since 1919. After having a &lt;a href=&quot;http://franksjewellers.ca/old/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;basic website&lt;/a&gt; for nearly a decade, owner, Bob Franks, realized that against the crowd sourced information of Yelp and improving competitor websites, Frank&amp;#39;s Jewellers needed a more effective website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob was one of our first clients for &lt;a href=&quot;/project/teknically-webplio/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Webplio&lt;/a&gt; back in Fall 2013 so it was a pleasure to work with him and their staff again. Built on Wordpress, I heavily customized a base theme in PHP, coded page templates, wrote new sales copy, built a custom Google Analytics dashboard, and trained staff how to edit content and understand Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new site is extremely easy to edit, cost efficient to maintain long term, and is beautifully responsive on any device. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The new website just looks fantastic and it even kept with our look and feel that we use in other marketing. After the training from Andrew, we&amp;#39;ve been uploading new diamonds when they come in and even been getting some new customers as a result. Couldn&amp;#39;t recommend him enough!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; - Bob Frank, Owner&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As young couples continue to trust Bob with their engagement rings, more of them will be learning about Bob through their new website. Check it out at &lt;a href=&quot;http://franksjewellers.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;franksjewellers.ca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2015 12:04:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/project/franks-jewellers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/project/franks-jewellers/</guid>
        
        <category>HTML/CSS</category>
        
        <category>PHP</category>
        
        <category>sales-copy</category>
        
        <category>wordpress</category>
        
        <category>training</category>
        
        <category>sysadmin</category>
        
        
        <category>project</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Canadian Fintech Startups Have Only 3 Options</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Assembled on July 7th were the Chief Digital Officers of Canada&amp;#39;s biggest banks (TD, CIBC, BMO, and Scotiabank) to discuss financial technology startups (fintech) at Communitech. Clearer than ever was the truth that though there&amp;#39;s lots of problems in Canadian banking ripe for disruption by startups, the opportunity is very limited. Canadian banks can&amp;#39;t innovate and are on the prowl for the startups that can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Update: Globe &amp; Mail Finance Reporter Agrees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long time finance reporter for the Globe &amp;amp; Mail agreed that fintech startups will be significantly cut out from truly disrupting the Canadian banks in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Andrew_Paradi&quot;&gt;@Andrew_Paradi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/globeinvestor&quot;&gt;@globeinvestor&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Uber&quot;&gt;@uber&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#10;Not banking, but maybe borrowing for clientele that can&amp;#39;t access a home-equity line of credit.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rob Carrick (@rcarrick) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rcarrick/status/634722889548365824&quot;&gt;August 21, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Slow Banks will be Slow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost every answer from the CDOs of TD, CIBC, BMO, and Scotiabank was laced with the underlying reality that innovation would not come from within their organizations. Bureaucratic corporate cultures, intense federal regulation, a buyers market in bank competition, and slow advances into Canada from external technologies make innovation a unique challenge for the Canadian banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire panel of CDOs knew the features that consumers wanted whether it was easier transfers to other people, contactless payments, or more powerful mobile apps. Yet they had few explanations for why these relatively simple fixes for an awful banking experience weren&amp;#8217;t already in place. &lt;a href=&quot;https://squareup.com/ca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Square&lt;/a&gt; has solved easy transfers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/apple-pay/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Apple Pay&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://officialandroid.blogspot.ca/2015/05/pay-your-way-with-android.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Android Pay&lt;/a&gt; standardize the most convenient payment technologies yet. And you only need to give &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mint.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mint&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acorns.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Acorns&lt;/a&gt; a try to understand just how much the bank&amp;#8217;s online and mobile experiences could improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-07-27-canadian-fintech-startups-have-only-3-options/Portfolio-Allocation-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Acorns investing for iOS &amp;amp; Android: both gorgeous design and an innovative approach to investing. Both of which you won&amp;#39;t find in big bank apps. &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#39;https://www.acorns.com/&amp;#39; target=&amp;#39;_blank&amp;#39;&amp;gt;https://www.acorns.com/&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banks whether limited by regulation, Apple Pay&amp;#8217;s rollout schedule, or &amp;#8220;design by committee&amp;#8221; internal bureaucracy, are desperate for startups to do the innovation that they can&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Banks Want to Become Amazon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a world where all transaction data on what, where, when, how, (and possibly even why) you buy was leveraged by the banks to target you for their services, new products, or even sold through an API to other companies. Currently this only happens on a limited scale by individual retailers who collect and leverage data in loyalty programs and to manage inventory (think PC Points or the recommendations you get on Amazon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this future envisioned by the banks, they would singularly hold all of your purchase information. What we&amp;#8217;ve seen from loyalty programs so far would just be the tip of the iceberg for the types of personalization that would be possible with the banks&amp;#8217; information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you thought PC Points offering you 200pts to eat a dozen bananas was too personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The panel reiterated over and over how important the analysis of transaction information and banking data is to their strategy. The banks don&amp;#8217;t just want to become commoditized transaction intermediaries like VISA or MasterCard. They want to become APIs for consumer purchasing information, so entrenched in the space that they can&amp;#8217;t be disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banks already collect and store these mountains of data, they just need ways to pull out insights while keeping a balance between personalization and privacy. The opportunity for fintech startups to solve this problem is huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tremors of Disruption in Words Unsaid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked about their 5 year forecast for Canadian banks one CDO mused that &amp;#8220;of course in &lt;em&gt;5 years&lt;/em&gt; we will still have brick &amp;amp; mortar branches.&amp;#8221; Implicitly, he points to a potentially inevitable time when there are banks that don&amp;#8217;t have branches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-07-27-canadian-fintech-startups-have-only-3-options/brick-mortar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brick &amp;amp;amp; mortar bank branches may fade over the long term but aren&amp;#39;t going anywhere according to the Canadian banking executives.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tangerine (formerly ING Direct) was the first glimmer of a future where opening accounts, transferring funds, and investing could all be done easily online without dealing with any bank staff. A bank that had a user experience as easy and pain-free as Uber would certainly attract my business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, unlike the transportation bylaws that Uber lobbies against, Canadian banking regulations would be significantly more difficult for an innovator to overcome. Federal regulation instead of local bylaws would render a divide and conquer &lt;a href=&quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/2015/7/27/9035731/future-of-uber-regulation-illegal-violations&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;city by city attack&lt;/a&gt; useless. Where Uber could simply skip &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/nevada-bans-uber-2014-11&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Las&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/2015/7/27/9035731/future-of-uber-regulation-illegal-violations&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vegas&lt;/a&gt; and move onto another city when lawsuits made Uber illegal, the dodging whack-a-mole routine doesn&amp;#8217;t work when lawsuits and judgements come down at a federal level. Simply ask &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/2014/6/25/5842524/what-does-the-aereo-ruling-mean-for-television&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aereo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-07-27-canadian-fintech-startups-have-only-3-options/tangerine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Even innovative upstart ING Direct with strong online-first banking growth over a decade still ended in acquisition. Scotiabank acquired ING Direct for over $3.1 billion in 2012 and rebranded it as Tangerine soon after. Feature advances have stalled since purchase.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tangerine was only possible because established bank, ING, expanded into Canada in 1997 with enough resources to deal with the regulation. With expansive established business around the world, they could pay to get over the regulatory hurdles keeping them from Canadian customers. Most startups will never start with a war chest big enough to get past the regulation to truly disrupt the banking experience in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Three Options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruption in banking is limited, internal bank innovation nearly impossible, so the banks need fintech startups more than ever. Canadian fintech startups now need to live with the fact that the odds for building a sustainable company in Canadian banking are even longer than imagined. The way I see it, there are three options for Canadian fintech: build a nimble firm and accept limited market growth opportunity, make the irrational assumption of founding a startup solely for acquisition, or dare to do the impossible; disrupt the Canadian banks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 10:59:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/blog/canadian-fintech-startups-have-only-3-options/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/blog/canadian-fintech-startups-have-only-3-options/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Favourite 6 Books Since January</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I purchased my Kobo Aura on Boxing Day 2014 and decided I would be more diligent in my leisure reading this year. 6 months in, these are the 6 books that I would most recommend. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;David &amp; Goliath - Malcolm Gladwell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-06-12-leisure-reading-part-1/Gladwell_David-and-Goliath.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Gladwell&amp;#39;s books have always intrigued me since I read about 10,000 hours to success in &lt;strong&gt;Outliers&lt;/strong&gt; in grade 9. &lt;strong&gt;David &amp;amp; Goliath&lt;/strong&gt; obliterates some of the most closely held beliefs about how diminishing returns really play out in society. As seems to be Malcolm&amp;#39;s style, each chapter digs deep into a single story as it relate&amp;#39;s to the book&amp;#39;s overarching theme. It certainly gave me a lot to think about across countless areas including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are smaller class sizes always the best investment to improve education?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it better long term to study at prestigious or less competitive university?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could the children of the very rich be as disadvantaged as the children of the very poor?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script id=&quot;infogram_0_how_society_really_works&quot; src=&quot;//e.infogr.am/js/embed.js?tdf&quot; type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;border-top:1px solid #acacac;padding-top:3px;font-family:Arial;font-size:10px;text-align:center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://infogr.am/how_society_really_works&quot; style=&quot;color:#acacac;text-decoration:none;&quot;&gt;How Society Really Works&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a style=&quot;color:#acacac;text-decoration:none;&quot; href=&quot;https://infogr.am&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Create infographics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach many policy issues more skeptically now. More money and resources will not always make things better when many aspects of society play out as Laffer curves and not traditional logarithmic diminishing returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Rosie Project - Graeme C. Simsion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-06-12-leisure-reading-part-1/The-Rosie-Project.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
While I was reading this book, it was all I could talk about. Maybe I&amp;#39;m just a sucker for a classic love story but I agree with Bill Gates (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gatesnotes.com/About-Bill-Gates/6-Books-I-Would-Recommend-Summer-Reading&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gatesnotes.com/Books/The-Rosie-Effect&quot; taget=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;) that this book is different. The book tells the tale of a biology professor with undiagnosed Aspergers syndrome that sets out on a journey to find the perfect wife by getting women to fill out a survey. Simsion did an unbelievable job writing the perfect internal thoughts of a near purely logical mind (and I found myself laughing as I admitted to myself that I shared many thought processes with a supposedly undiagnosed Aspergers professor). I very rarely read fiction but the The Rosie Project made me want to again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. As with most things, the sequel isn&amp;#39;t as good as the original but the Rosie Effect is still worth the read. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Related books I enjoyed:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Little Brother - Cory Doctorow (&lt;a href=&quot;http://craphound.com/littlebrother/download/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Free download&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/strong&gt; It was just as exciting to read now as it was when I first read it in grade 9. For anybody who&amp;#39;s been reading about Edward Snowden and the disintegrating state of privacy in society, this fiction set in the near future seems closer to reality with each passing year. Looking forward to an encryption key swap with all of you soon!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Autobiography of Malcolm X - Malcolm X &amp; Alex Haley&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-06-12-leisure-reading-part-1/Autobiography-Of-Malcolm-X-The.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malcolm X grew up like many African American males. He went through the foster system, spent his youth in the ghetto, hustled drugs in Harlem, and ended up in jail. Yet these undistinguishable formative years are what make the rest of his life so profound. He overcome religious cults to become a widely known and respected civil rights and community leader in Harlem. His powerful, passionate speeches live on in recordings and videos today long past his assassination in February 1965.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sentiment shared repeatedly throughout the book was his belief that the desegregationist civil rights protestors like Martin Luther King Jr. weren&amp;#39;t going to affect lasting change, but could simply tackle surface issues. Repeal of Jim Crow laws, integrated busses, integrated schools, the Civil Rights Act of 1964... &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/features/archive/2014/05/the-case-for-reparations/361631/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;it was all just lipstick on a pig&lt;/a&gt;. Fundamental complex race problems couldn&amp;#39;t be dealt with simply with integration and legislation. As we continue to see the racially charged police abuses in Ferguson &amp;amp; Baltimore, and the silent discriminating economic issues around education funding, health care access, and poverty rates, I have begun to understand that &amp;quot;radical&amp;quot; Malcolm may not have been so radical after all. &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fby2koTK4lY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;We shall overcome&lt;/a&gt;, but we certainly have not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Related books I enjoyed:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unbroken - Laura Hillenbrand:&lt;/strong&gt; Gave me much better insight into the Pacific Theatre of World War II and Louie&amp;#39;s determination was genuinely inspiring. As with most things, this book was better than the 2014 movie directed by Angelina Jolie.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Meaning of Marriage - Tim Keller&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-06-12-leisure-reading-part-1/meaning-marriage-tim-keller.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Though I&amp;#39;m many years away from ever exchanging rings, Tim&amp;#39;s book speaks wisdom to single, unmarried, and married couples. I found his strong use of data from research studies paired with Biblical references a better approach than most relationship books that just pull from the author&amp;#39;s personal experience and secular anecdotes. My favourite two pieces of data paraphrased were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The vast majority of the 45% divorce rate are those who marry before 18, are high school drop outs, or have a a baby together before marrying. &lt;strong&gt;If you don&amp;#39;t fall into those categories, your chances of a successful marriage are very high.&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hookingupsmart.com/2012/06/13/relationshipstrategies/your-chances-of-divorce-may-be-much-lower-than-you-think/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over 60% of marriages are described as &amp;#39;very happy&amp;#39;, over 66% of unhappy marriages will become happy within five years if the people stay married and don&amp;#39;t get divorced.(&lt;a href=&quot;http://americanvalues.org/catalog/pdfs/does_divorce_make_people_happy.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;strong&gt;Perseverance pays off even more often than I thought.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Related books I enjoyed:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things I Wish I&amp;#39;d Known Before We Got Married - Gary Chapman:&lt;/strong&gt; Gary covers the 5 Love Languages, dealing with in-laws, and other practical issues that often come up in the first couple years. Short but worthwhile read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Prodigal God - Tim Keller:&lt;/strong&gt; Tim examines how the classic parable in Luke 15:11-32 is such a powerful expose of how powerful God&amp;#39;s love is and how contrary to societal expectations it is even today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/timothy-keller-podcast/id352660924?mt=2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tim Keller Podcast - Tim Keller&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; This has been my go to podcast while I&amp;#39;ve been working out. Tim masterfully weaves philosophical and Biblical ideas together into thought provoking talks. The most convicting ones I&amp;#39;ve listened to so far have been &amp;quot;Your Plans: God&amp;#39;s Plans&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Praying our Fears&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;Praying our Tears&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Hard Thing About Hard Things - Ben Horowitz&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-06-12-leisure-reading-part-1/hard-things-ben-horowitz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hand down, this is the most practical management book I&amp;#39;ve ever read.&lt;/strong&gt; Written with the brevity of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt; but interspersed with rap lyrics, Ben Horowitz (startup founder, CEO, and famous VC) dishes on how to effectively manage a startup. I valued the lessons and perspective he had from over a decade building a startup, IPO-ing during the Dotcom crash of 2000, and building Opsware into a massive IT software business that was acquired by  HP for $1.6 billion in 2006. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on Teknically, certain aspects were always easy to identify as potential causes of our failure. After reading Hard Things, it is so much easier to pinpoint what specifically went wrong and what I will do differently in a new startup. &lt;strong&gt;This book is simply the most practical, must read for any startup founder.&lt;/strong&gt; It succeeds Zero to One as my must-read recommendation for anybody in startups right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Losing the Signal - Jacquie McNish &amp; Sean Silcoff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-06-12-leisure-reading-part-1/losin_the_signal_mcnish.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought Losing the Signal on Kobo days after it came out and &lt;strong&gt;was finished reading it within 10 days.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;#39;s the riveting account of Mike Lazaridis, Jim Balsille, RIM&amp;#39;s hard fought rise to dominance in the smartphone industry they invented, and their precipitous fall we have all witnessed in the past 6 years. There are two reasons why I found this book so difficult to put down. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, reading of how RIM was built right here in Waterloo where I work, live, and study was like reading my own family history. So much of the Kitchener Waterloo tech scene has been impacted by RIM and built by former RIM employees. So many different businesses and locations mentioned in the book I recognized or had been to myself, it became so easy and surreal to visualize these thrilling events that happened so close to where I live. &lt;strong&gt;Understanding the story of RIM is fundamental in many ways to understanding the story of the Kitchener Waterloo tech scene.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;strong&gt;Losing the Signal&lt;/strong&gt; provided the inside story of what went wrong. Having just read &lt;strong&gt;The Hard Thing About Hard Things&lt;/strong&gt;, I more precisely could identify the management debt that grew so large that even if the iPhone hadn&amp;#39;t disrupted the smartphone industry, RIM still would not have been in good shape. Leo Tolstoy writes &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Happy families are all alike; every unhappy family is unhappy in its own way.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; I think the same is true for startup success. Every unsuccessful startup is unsuccessful in its own way. There were certain aspects of RIM&amp;#39;s downward spiral that I immediately recognized because at Teknically we had unsuccessfully dealt with the same issue. Yet many others were unique to RIM. In both cases it can be depressing to dwell on what could have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Epilogue, Jim Balsille grew increasingly frustrated as he recalled his final years at RIM where he had pushed for a focus on software &amp;amp; services (specifically cross platform BBM). His plan was dismissed by Mike Lazaridis, the board, and was later shuttered by RIM&amp;#39;s next CEO, Thorsten Heins. After Jim resigned, he watched Facebook acquire WhatsApp for $22 billion, Kik and weChat continue to explode, and the messaging, software &amp;amp; services market prove to be more promising than almost every hardware company other than Apple and Samsung. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pride and ignorant optimism let RIM&amp;#39;s management believe that new smart phones and QNX powered Blackberry 10 would save them. To know the clear promise of Jim&amp;#39;s BBM software &amp;amp; services strategy and yet see how viciously it was pushed aside is, for me, the most profound indication of RIM management&amp;#39;s misunderstanding of the new world ushered in by the iPhone. &lt;strong&gt;A market where apps are more important than battery life, design matters more than productivity, and cloud services are better consumer lock in than a perfect hardware keyboard.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Next Reads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 12 books done in 6 months, I&amp;#39;m on track for a book every two weeks. Right now I&amp;#39;m working on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elon Musk: Tesla, SpaceX, and the Quest for a Fantastic Future by Ashlee Vance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Hobbit by J. R. R. Tolkien&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter how busy you feel you are, it&amp;#39;s always the right time to start investing in yourself by reading. I never set out to reach a certain number but Im glad that I stuck with reading for fun this year. The dividends continue to pay out in my life and I hope the same for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next in Series: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/leisure-reading-part-2&quot;&gt;Best Books since June&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 21:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/blog/leisure-reading-part-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/blog/leisure-reading-part-1/</guid>
        
        <category>life</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fred &amp; Ted: Uber&#39;s Disruption is Delusional</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Three key insights on Uber, when to drop out, and valuations from Communitech&amp;#39;s fireside chat with renowned VC Fred &amp;amp; CEO Ted.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Woah who&amp;#39;s Fred &amp;amp; Ted?!&lt;/strong&gt; Fred Wilson is a very well known Venture Capitalist and Co-Founder of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usv.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Union Square Ventures&lt;/a&gt; (funded Twitter, Tumblr, Etsy, Kik...). Ted Livingston is Founder/CEO of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kik.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kik&lt;/a&gt;, currently the messaging app of choice for over 200 million people. As an early investor in Kik, Fred &amp;amp; Ted have built a strong working relationship and it was remarkable to have both of them sit down to share their perspective with a chat moderated by &lt;a href=&quot;http://velocity.uwaterloo.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Velocity&lt;/a&gt; Director Mike Kirkup. Three parts of the chat stood out for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Disruption is Delusional&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anybody reading the news over the past two years has seen the controversies as a result of two companies disrupting the transportation and accommodation sectors respectively: &lt;strong&gt;Uber &amp;amp; Airbnb. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-05-11-fred-ted/airbnb-nyc-poster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Defaced Airbnb Poster in New York City, July 2014.  Photo: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#39;http://d.fastcompany.net/multisite_files/fastcompany/poster/2014/07/3033191-poster-p-1-airbnb-ads-guerilla-vigilante.jpg&amp;#39; target=&amp;#39;_blank&amp;#39;&amp;gt;FastCompany&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From most recently a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/alberta/calgary-home-in-ruins-after-airbnb-nightmare/article24182387/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;drug-induced orgy&amp;quot; at an Airbnb in Calgary&lt;/a&gt; to an &lt;a href=&quot;http://valleywag.gawker.com/uber-calls-womans-20-mile-nightmare-abduction-an-ineff-1645819700&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Uber driver kidnapping a woman&lt;/a&gt;, entire sites have sprung up devoted to frightening tales including &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.airbnbhell.com/airbnb-guest-stories/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;airbnbHell&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href&quot;http://www.ubertrocity.com/top-10-uber-horror-stories/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UberTrocity&lt;/a&gt;. These companies have tried to combat horror stories with self-justifying &lt;a href=&quot;http://pando.com/2012/10/24/travis-shrugged/?utm_content=buffera9b1c&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ayn Rand philosophies&lt;/a&gt; instilled into employees and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/2014/7/14/5896785/hey-new-york-airbnb-wants-to-get-you-in-bed&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; persuasive marketing campaigns&lt;/a&gt; to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked about his thoughts on these companies, Fred didn&amp;#39;t let them off the hook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;There are things that Airbnb has facilitated that aren&amp;#39;t good things.  I&amp;#39;m not an investor in them so I can admit it. [...] I think the same thing is true for some ride sharing services. [...] We ought to admit it&amp;#39;s not a good thing. We ought to start to have a conversation with people about how we can put the proper controls in place so that these services are used in ways that are helpful, and are not used in ways that are harmful.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet despite the horrific situations that users have found themselves in, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://upstart.bizjournals.com/entrepreneurs/hot-shots/2014/11/05/travis-kalanicks-take-no-prisoners-startup.html?page=all&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;companies&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomberg.com/bw/articles/2014-02-20/uber-leads-taxi-industry-disruption-amid-fight-for-riders-drivers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;claim&lt;/a&gt; that this is simply the price of &lt;em&gt;disruption&lt;/em&gt;. I have used both services and they indeed are radically better than their &amp;quot;old economy&amp;quot; equivalents. It can become easy to justify the horrific experiences of some users as simply an unfortunate &lt;em&gt;cost of doing business&lt;/em&gt; in the shared economy. Yet, Fred wasn&amp;#39;t silent on the valley culture of &lt;em&gt;disruption&lt;/em&gt; worship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I don&amp;#39;t like when people in my business or in the startup sector are blindly like &amp;#39;We&amp;#39;re disruptors!&amp;#39; &amp;#39;Screw those people, we&amp;#39;re making the world better!&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;Get off our back&amp;#39;. It&amp;#39;s not really true. There&amp;#39;s always some harm when you build something new and it does, I think, make sense to have a conversation about what the rules of the game should be to make sure that things are safe and things are done properly.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred&amp;#39;s remarks struck a chord with me in his balanced approach to the need for &lt;strong&gt;reasonable yet protective&lt;/strong&gt; regulation in the new sharing economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Don&#39;t Choose to Drop Out, Wait for the Startup to Force You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A question that was brought up by Velocity Director Mike Kirkup and that echoes frequently in the minds of student entrepreneurs is &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;how do I know if I should drop out?&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;. We asked ourselves this a lot prior to pulling the plug and &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrewparadi.com/2014/10/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;deferring classes&lt;/a&gt; in Fall 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-05-11-fred-ted/ted-livingston-kik-phone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ted with early Kik apps after raising his Series A in 2011. Photo: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#39;http://betakit.com/39411/&amp;#39; target=&amp;#39;_blank&amp;#39;&amp;gt;BetaKit&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many entrepreneurs (myself included) who sometimes seem like they&amp;#39;re looking for a reason to drop out, Ted stayed in school as long as he could. &lt;strong&gt;He didn&amp;#39;t drop out of University of Waterloo until Kik was raising a $1 million seed funding round.&lt;/strong&gt; At that point, his investors wouldn&amp;#39;t sign unless he dropped out to work full time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He and Mike chimed in about the world leading talent pool at University of Waterloo and opportunities to do startups without giving up the safety net of university. All three on stage reiterated that you shouldn&amp;#39;t start a startup to simply start a startup, wait for the right idea and work at other startups until then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone through many of these realizations over &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/lessons-from-behind-the-curtain/&quot;&gt;my journey with Teknically&lt;/a&gt;, I couldn&amp;#39;t agree more with the panel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t drop out until you absolutely have to. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t start a startup just to start a startup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t take for granted the safety net of being a university student, make the most of it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Let the Valuation Choose You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few minutes of the talk, Fred was asked about how to choose an initial valuation for fundraising rounds. He proceeded to dish out one of the simplest mathematical methods I&amp;#39;ve heard. (If the following section seems a bit confusing, try this &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/EHzvmyMJEK4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to Start a Startup lecture&lt;/a&gt;, if it seems too simple check out the book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0470929820/domofa-20&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Venture Deals&lt;/a&gt; by Brad Feld)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most entrepreneurs initially want to optimize for a high valuation when raising money. This mentality stems from the desire to give less of their company away for the same amount of money. Fred reiterated that this is optimizing for the wrong thing. Instead of simply of choosing a big valuation and trying to justify it, he suggested to focus on three more important areas to easily determine a reasonable valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much do you want to give away?&lt;/strong&gt; Each round plan to give 10-20% of the company away, but don&amp;#39;t go too much over 20% or later rounds will become very difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much do you need?&lt;/strong&gt; At least 12 months of runway. More than 18 may make the round difficult to raise and harder for next one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose the right investors.&lt;/strong&gt; At the end of the day who your investors are matter more than valuation, you&amp;#39;ll be married to them most likely for the lifespan of the company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculate your valuation simply: &lt;br/&gt;Valuation = 12-18 month burn / 10-20% equity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Example A&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raising (burn)&lt;/strong&gt; $20,000 x 12 months = $240,000 &lt;strong&gt;for (equity)&lt;/strong&gt; 10-20%.
&lt;strong&gt;Valuation&lt;/strong&gt; = $240,000 / 0.2 to $240,000/0.1 = $1.2 million to $2.4 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Example B&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raising&lt;/strong&gt; $50,000 x 18 months = $900,000 &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; 15%
&lt;strong&gt;Valuation&lt;/strong&gt; = $900,000 / 0.15 = $6 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred&amp;#39;s simple math makes choosing a ballpark valuation almost too easy. We now have no excuse for getting sucked into an valuation inflation spiral (I&amp;#39;m looking at you &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/a9ToqUSfkv8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt; Season 2 Episode 1)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Last Words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fireside Chats = Free learning from legends (usually worth the hype, don&amp;#39;t let doubts stop you from showing up!)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 14:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/blog/fred-ted/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/blog/fred-ted/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Innovation in the 6</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thousands of entrepreneurs, researchers, policy makers, and community organizations coming together to celebrate and foster innovation in Ontario. On April 27th, I went to OCE Discovery 2015 in Toronto.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Founder&#39;s Forum with a Dragon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2014, Teknically (see part &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-dream-fades/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;) was approved for $30,000 in Ontario Centres of Excellence (OCE) SmartStart funding. The funding allowed us to work full time developing Webplio for small business owners in Ontario and around the world in Fall 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year in April, OCE hosts the Discovery conference at the Toronto Metro Convention Centre to celebrate the innovation that funded companies have produced in the past year. I attended to represent Teknically at the exclusive Founder&amp;#39;s Forum event before the conference opened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-29-innovation-in-the-6/Croxon_Bruce.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bruce Croxon: Founder of Lavalife, Dragon on Dragon&amp;#39;s Den Season 6-8. Photo: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#39;http://www.techvibes.com/blog/why-bruce-croxon-dragons-den-2014-03-17&amp;#39; target=&amp;#39;_blank&amp;#39;&amp;gt;TechVibes&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bruce Croxon anchored the event with an initial talk and panel discussion afterwards. He seemed very down to earth and honest in ways I hadn&amp;#39;t heard before from other entrepreneurs. One thing he said stood out for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he looks back on the 16 years building Lavalife until it&amp;#39;s $180 million acquisition, he doesn&amp;#39;t know whether he would recommend becoming an entrepreneur to his young children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most entrepreneurs I&amp;#39;ve heard always say something along the lines of &amp;quot;well, there were ups and downs but at the end of the day I&amp;#39;d do it all again&amp;quot;. Of course what Bruce said is up to interpretation, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; I think it hints at the truth that &lt;strong&gt;money isn&amp;#39;t everything.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sacrificing often over a decade to build a startup isn&amp;#39;t just long hours and high stress at low compensation. It&amp;#39;s the lost opportunities to enjoy your youth, travel, build a family, or simply have any type of balance in your life. For a few entrepreneurs like Bruce, all of this leads to a huge acquisition payout or equity worth millions. &lt;strong&gt;For most it doesn&amp;#39;t. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know first hand how quickly a startup can take over your life. &lt;strong&gt;In Fall 2014, I was easily clocking 12-16 hour days, sometimes longer.&lt;/strong&gt; I thrived with the fast pace and enjoyed the hard work we were doing but I can say now I&amp;#39;m thankful it ended when it did. I love my family, friends, and enjoy salsa dancing, piano, guitar, and reading. All of these were sacrificed in part or whole while I was building a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Bruce, I&amp;#39;m not sure I would make that sacrifice again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Second most profound insight from Bruce: &amp;quot;Nobody changes past the age of 11. Don&amp;#39;t hire or do anything assuming people will change&amp;quot;. Real.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;BOSI: Discovering I&#39;m a Builder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In first year BBA at Laurier students test their emotional intelligence with DISC, EQI, MyersBriggs, and any number of other tests. Most of these are very broad in scope and just provide general insights into who you are and who you are best suited to work with on a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a breakout session at Discovery, I learned about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bosidna.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BOSI&lt;/a&gt;: the test to determine your Entrepreneurial DNA. It gave me a much clearer understanding of situations in which I thrive and blind spots that can hold me back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/fsU9N6A18sY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Entrepreneurial DNA&amp;quot; annotation=&amp;quot;BOSI Creator, Joe Abraham, speaking at TedxBend. Alt link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fsU9N6A18sY&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/fsU9N6A18sY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to BOSI, the four types of entrepreneurs are (by % of total entrepreneurs):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15%   Builder&lt;/strong&gt;: High scale &amp;amp; sustainable, mostly $5+ million businesses, controlling. Decision Lens: infrastructure. Biggest struggle: relationships. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Donald Trump.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;30% Opportunist&lt;/strong&gt;: Right place = ground floor, willing to get on any rocket, optimistic, multiple personal revenue streams. Decision lens: financial freedom. Biggest struggle: focus. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Richard Branson.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;42% Specialist&lt;/strong&gt;: Expert, single industry. Decision lens: reputation. Biggest struggle: lead generation. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Bill Gates.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13% Innovator&lt;/strong&gt;: Mad scientist, aha moment, in the lab, limitless IP. Decision lens: impact/mission. Biggest struggle: operations. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Mark Zuckerberg.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking my own assessment it was clarifying to recognize that my primary DNA type was Builder and secondary was Opportunist. Looking back on my favourite aspects of positions in clubs, organizations, and Teknically, they were all situations in which a Builder would thrive. They were situations in which I thrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BOSI gave me a new lens to view other entrepreneurs and myself. It also provided some initial ideas on how I can find opportunities better suited to my strengths. You can take the ten question test yourself &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bosidna.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;d highly recommend taking the two minutes to fill it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Real Networking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody always talks about networking especially at business schools. The focus is always on how networking can land you the dream job, help you meet famous business people, or give you connections to power. I think much of this encourages an approach that is self-centered and doesn&amp;#39;t provide either person value. It simply leads to constant self-promotion and business card exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with most things in life, I&amp;#39;ve begun to learn first hand that serving others is much better than serving yourself. At Discovery it was awesome to reconnect with entrepreneurs and mentors I&amp;#39;ve met along my journey in the KW Tech community. It was even cooler to sit and talk with entrepreneurs I hadn&amp;#39;t met before and learn how they are innovating in areas from an &lt;a href=&quot;http://dymaxiainc.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;anxiety alert system for people with autism&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shocklock.ca/#/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;car maintenance safety hardware&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I wasn&amp;#39;t working on Webplio anymore, there was no distraction to try and get the person to sign up. I was able to listen and think of the best insights or lessons I could share to help them. I can&amp;#39;t speak for others but I found this approach to networking much more rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The State of Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-29-innovation-in-the-6/oce-founder-forum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an honour to attend these events with so many hard working, down to earth people. I didn&amp;#39;t know what to expect at Discovery but I walked away very impressed with the individuals in many aspects of Ontario&amp;#39;s entrepreneurship ecosystem, the growing synergy between government and startup sector, and the state of innovation in Ontario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am more convinced than ever that Ontario is one of the best places to build a startup. Innovation isn&amp;#39;t confined to &amp;quot;the valley&amp;quot;, it&amp;#39;s happening right here in KW, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fxTyS-aqdLE?t=8s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the 6&lt;/a&gt;, and all across Ontario.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 19:47:45 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>//andrewparadi.com/blog/innovation-in-the-6/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//andrewparadi.com/blog/innovation-in-the-6/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
