<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Andrew Paradi</title>
    <description>Growth Focused Front End Developer
</description>
    <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://andrewparadi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 01:01:03 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2015 01:01:03 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fred &amp; Ted: Uber&#39;s Disruption is Delusional</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Three key insights on Uber, when to drop out, and valuations from Communitech&amp;#39;s fireside chat with renowned VC Fred &amp;amp; CEO Ted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Woah who&amp;#39;s Fred &amp;amp; Ted?!&lt;/strong&gt; Fred Wilson is a very well known Venture Capitalist and Co-Founder of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usv.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Union Square Ventures&lt;/a&gt; (funded Twitter, Tumblr, Etsy, Kik...). Ted Livingston is Founder/CEO of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kik.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kik&lt;/a&gt;, currently the messaging app of choice for over 200 million people. As an early investor in Kik, Fred &amp;amp; Ted have built a strong working relationship and it was remarkable to have both of them sit down to share their perspective with a chat moderated by &lt;a href=&quot;http://velocity.uwaterloo.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Velocity&lt;/a&gt; Director Mike Kirkup. Three parts of the chat stood out for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Disruption is Delusional&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anybody reading the news over the past two years has seen the controversies as a result of two companies disrupting the transportation and accommodation sectors respectively: &lt;strong&gt;Uber &amp;amp; Airbnb. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-05-11-fred-ted/airbnb-nyc-poster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Defaced Airbnb Poster in New York City, July 2014.  Photo: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#39;http://d.fastcompany.net/multisite_files/fastcompany/poster/2014/07/3033191-poster-p-1-airbnb-ads-guerilla-vigilante.jpg&amp;#39; target=&amp;#39;_blank&amp;#39;&amp;gt;FastCompany&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From most recently a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/alberta/calgary-home-in-ruins-after-airbnb-nightmare/article24182387/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;drug-induced orgy&amp;quot; at an Airbnb in Calgary&lt;/a&gt; to an &lt;a href=&quot;http://valleywag.gawker.com/uber-calls-womans-20-mile-nightmare-abduction-an-ineff-1645819700&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Uber driver kidnapping a woman&lt;/a&gt;, entire sites have sprung up devoted to frightening tales including &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.airbnbhell.com/airbnb-guest-stories/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;airbnbHell&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href&quot;http://www.ubertrocity.com/top-10-uber-horror-stories/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UberTrocity&lt;/a&gt;. These companies have tried to combat horror stories with self-justifying &lt;a href=&quot;http://pando.com/2012/10/24/travis-shrugged/?utm_content=buffera9b1c&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ayn Rand philosophies&lt;/a&gt; instilled into employees and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/2014/7/14/5896785/hey-new-york-airbnb-wants-to-get-you-in-bed&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; persuasive marketing campaigns&lt;/a&gt; to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked about his thoughts on these companies, Fred didn&amp;#39;t let them off the hook:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;There are things that Airbnb has facilitated that aren&amp;#39;t good things.  I&amp;#39;m not an investor in them so I can admit it. [...] I think the same thing is true for some ride sharing services. [...] We ought to admit it&amp;#39;s not a good thing. We ought to start to have a conversation with people about how we can put the proper controls in place so that these services are used in ways that are helpful, and are not used in ways that are harmful.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet despite the horrific situations that users have found themselves in, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://upstart.bizjournals.com/entrepreneurs/hot-shots/2014/11/05/travis-kalanicks-take-no-prisoners-startup.html?page=all&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;companies&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomberg.com/bw/articles/2014-02-20/uber-leads-taxi-industry-disruption-amid-fight-for-riders-drivers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;claim&lt;/a&gt; that this is simply the price of &lt;em&gt;disruption&lt;/em&gt;. I have used both services and they indeed are radically better than their &amp;quot;old economy&amp;quot; equivalents. It can become easy to justify the horrific experiences of some users as simply an unfortunate &lt;em&gt;cost of doing business&lt;/em&gt; in the shared economy. Yet, Fred wasn&amp;#39;t silent on the valley culture of &lt;em&gt;disruption&lt;/em&gt; worship:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I don&amp;#39;t like when people in my business or in the startup sector are blindly like &amp;#39;We&amp;#39;re disruptors!&amp;#39; &amp;#39;Screw those people, we&amp;#39;re making the world better!&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;Get off our back&amp;#39;. It&amp;#39;s not really true. There&amp;#39;s always some harm when you build something new and it does, I think, make sense to have a conversation about what the rules of the game should be to make sure that things are safe and things are done properly.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred&amp;#39;s remarks struck a chord with me in his balanced approach to the need for &lt;strong&gt;reasonable yet protective&lt;/strong&gt; regulation in the new sharing economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Don&#39;t Choose to Drop Out, Wait for the Startup to Force You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A question that was brought up by Velocity Director Mike Kirkup and that echoes frequently in the minds of student entrepreneurs is &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;how do I know if I should drop out?&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;. We asked ourselves this a lot prior to pulling the plug and &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrewparadi.com/2014/10/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;deferring classes&lt;/a&gt; in Fall 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-05-11-fred-ted/ted-livingston-kik-phone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ted with early Kik apps after raising his Series A in 2011. Photo: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#39;http://betakit.com/39411/&amp;#39; target=&amp;#39;_blank&amp;#39;&amp;gt;BetaKit&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many entrepreneurs (myself included) who sometimes seem like they&amp;#39;re looking for a reason to drop out, Ted stayed in school as long as he could. &lt;strong&gt;He didn&amp;#39;t drop out of University of Waterloo until Kik was raising a $1 million seed funding round.&lt;/strong&gt; At that point, his investors wouldn&amp;#39;t sign unless he dropped out to work full time. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He and Mike chimed in about the world leading talent pool at University of Waterloo and opportunities to do startups without giving up the safety net of university. All three on stage reiterated that you shouldn&amp;#39;t start a startup to simply start a startup, wait for the right idea and work at other startups until then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having gone through many of these realizations over &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/lessons-from-behind-the-curtain/&quot;&gt;my journey with Teknically&lt;/a&gt;, I couldn&amp;#39;t agree more with the panel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t drop out until you absolutely have to. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t start a startup just to start a startup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;#39;t take for granted the safety net of being a university student, make the most of it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Let the Valuation Choose You&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few minutes of the talk, Fred was asked about how to choose an initial valuation for fundraising rounds. He proceeded to dish out one of the simplest mathematical methods I&amp;#39;ve heard. (If the following section seems a bit confusing, try this &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/EHzvmyMJEK4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to Start a Startup lecture&lt;/a&gt;, if it seems too simple check out the book &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0470929820/domofa-20&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Venture Deals&lt;/a&gt; by Brad Feld)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most entrepreneurs initially want to optimize for a high valuation when raising money. This mentality stems from the desire to give less of their company away for the same amount of money. Fred reiterated that this is optimizing for the wrong thing. Instead of simply of choosing a big valuation and trying to justify it, he suggested to focus on three more important areas to easily determine a reasonable valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much do you want to give away?&lt;/strong&gt; Each round plan to give 10-20% of the company away, but don&amp;#39;t go too much over 20% or later rounds will become very difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much do you need?&lt;/strong&gt; At least 12 months of runway. More than 18 may make the round difficult to raise and harder for next one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choose the right investors.&lt;/strong&gt; At the end of the day who your investors are matter more than valuation, you&amp;#39;ll be married to them most likely for the lifespan of the company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculate your valuation simply: &lt;br/&gt;Valuation = 12-18 month burn / 10-20% equity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Example A&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raising (burn)&lt;/strong&gt; $20,000 x 12 months = $240,000 &lt;strong&gt;for (equity)&lt;/strong&gt; 10-20%.
&lt;strong&gt;Valuation&lt;/strong&gt; = $240,000 / 0.2 to $240,000/0.1 = $1.2 million to $2.4 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Example B&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raising&lt;/strong&gt; $50,000 x 18 months = $900,000 &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; 15%
&lt;strong&gt;Valuation&lt;/strong&gt; = $900,000 / 0.15 = $6 million&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred&amp;#39;s simple math makes choosing a ballpark valuation almost too easy. We now have no excuse for getting sucked into an valuation inflation spiral (I&amp;#39;m looking at you &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/a9ToqUSfkv8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt; Season 2 Episode 1)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Last Words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fireside Chats = Free learning from legends (usually worth the hype, don&amp;#39;t let doubts stop you from showing up!)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2015 14:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/fred-ted/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/fred-ted/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Innovation in the 6</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Thousands of entrepreneurs, researchers, policy makers, and community organizations coming together to celebrate and foster innovation in Ontario. On April 27th, I went to OCE Discovery 2015 in Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Founder&#39;s Forum with a Dragon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2014, Teknically (see part &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-dream-fades/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;) was approved for $30,000 in Ontario Centres of Excellence (OCE) SmartStart funding. The funding allowed us to work full time developing Webplio for small business owners in Ontario and around the world in Fall 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year in April, OCE hosts the Discovery conference at the Toronto Metro Convention Centre to celebrate the innovation that funded companies have produced in the past year. I attended to represent Teknically at the exclusive Founder&amp;#39;s Forum event before the conference opened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-29-innovation-in-the-6/Croxon_Bruce.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bruce Croxon: Founder of Lavalife, Dragon on Dragon&amp;#39;s Den Season 6-8. Photo: &amp;lt;a href=&amp;#39;http://www.techvibes.com/blog/why-bruce-croxon-dragons-den-2014-03-17&amp;#39; target=&amp;#39;_blank&amp;#39;&amp;gt;TechVibes&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bruce Croxon anchored the event with an initial talk and panel discussion afterwards. He seemed very down to earth and honest in ways I hadn&amp;#39;t heard before from other entrepreneurs. One thing he said stood out for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he looks back on the 16 years building Lavalife until it&amp;#39;s $180 million acquisition, he doesn&amp;#39;t know whether he would recommend becoming an entrepreneur to his young children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most entrepreneurs I&amp;#39;ve heard always say something along the lines of &amp;quot;well, there were ups and downs but at the end of the day I&amp;#39;d do it all again&amp;quot;. Of course what Bruce said is up to interpretation, &lt;strong&gt;but&lt;/strong&gt; I think it hints at the truth that &lt;strong&gt;money isn&amp;#39;t everything.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sacrificing often over a decade to build a startup isn&amp;#39;t just long hours and high stress at low compensation. It&amp;#39;s the lost opportunities to enjoy your youth, travel, build a family, or simply have any type of balance in your life. For a few entrepreneurs like Bruce, all of this leads to a huge acquisition payout or equity worth millions. &lt;strong&gt;For most it doesn&amp;#39;t. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know first hand how quickly a startup can take over your life. &lt;strong&gt;In Fall 2014, I was easily clocking 12-16 hour days, sometimes longer.&lt;/strong&gt; I thrived with the fast pace and enjoyed the hard work we were doing but I can say now I&amp;#39;m thankful it ended when it did. I love my family, friends, and enjoy salsa dancing, piano, guitar, and reading. All of these were sacrificed in part or whole while I was building a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Bruce, I&amp;#39;m not sure I would make that sacrifice again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Second most profound insight from Bruce: &amp;quot;Nobody changes past the age of 11. Don&amp;#39;t hire or do anything assuming people will change&amp;quot;. Real.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;BOSI: Discovering I&#39;m a Builder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In first year BBA at Laurier students test their emotional intelligence with DISC, EQI, Myers–Briggs, and any number of other tests. Most of these are very broad in scope and just provide general insights into who you are and who you are best suited to work with on a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a breakout session at Discovery, I learned about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bosidna.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BOSI&lt;/a&gt;: the test to determine your Entrepreneurial DNA. It gave me a much clearer understanding of situations in which I thrive and blind spots that can hold me back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/fsU9N6A18sY?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Entrepreneurial DNA&amp;quot; annotation=&amp;quot;BOSI Creator, Joe Abraham, speaking at TedxBend. Alt link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fsU9N6A18sY&quot;&gt;https://youtu.be/fsU9N6A18sY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to BOSI, the four types of entrepreneurs are (by % of total entrepreneurs):
- &lt;strong&gt;15%   Builder&lt;/strong&gt;: High scale &amp;amp; sustainable, mostly $5+ million businesses, controlling. Decision Lens: infrastructure. Biggest struggle: relationships. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Donald Trump.&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;30% Opportunist&lt;/strong&gt;: Right place = ground floor, willing to get on any rocket, optimistic, multiple personal revenue streams. Decision lens: financial freedom. Biggest struggle: focus. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Richard Branson.&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;42% Specialist&lt;/strong&gt;: Expert, single industry. Decision lens: reputation. Biggest struggle: lead generation. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Bill Gates.&lt;/strong&gt;
- &lt;strong&gt;13% Innovator&lt;/strong&gt;: Mad scientist, aha moment, in the lab, limitless IP. Decision lens: impact/mission. Biggest struggle: operations. &lt;strong&gt;Given example: Mark Zuckerberg.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After taking my own assessment it was clarifying to recognize that my primary DNA type was Builder and secondary was Opportunist. Looking back on my favourite aspects of positions in clubs, organizations, and Teknically, they were all situations in which a Builder would thrive. They were situations in which I thrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BOSI gave me a new lens to view other entrepreneurs and myself. It also provided some initial ideas on how I can find opportunities better suited to my strengths. You can take the ten question test yourself &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bosidna.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;d highly recommend taking the two minutes to fill it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Real Networking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody always talks about networking especially at business schools. The focus is always on how networking can land you the dream job, help you meet famous business people, or give you connections to power. I think much of this encourages an approach that is self-centered and doesn&amp;#39;t provide either person value. It simply leads to constant self-promotion and business card exchanges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with most things in life, I&amp;#39;ve begun to learn first hand that serving others is much better than serving yourself. At Discovery it was awesome to reconnect with entrepreneurs and mentors I&amp;#39;ve met along my journey in the KW Tech community. It was even cooler to sit and talk with entrepreneurs I hadn&amp;#39;t met before and learn how they are innovating in areas from an &lt;a href=&quot;http://dymaxiainc.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;anxiety alert system for people with autism&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shocklock.ca/#/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;car maintenance safety hardware&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I wasn&amp;#39;t working on Webplio anymore, there was no distraction to try and get the person to sign up. I was able to listen and think of the best insights or lessons I could share to help them. I can&amp;#39;t speak for others but I found this approach to networking much more rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The State of Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-29-innovation-in-the-6/oce-founder-forum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an honour to attend these events with so many hard working, down to earth people. I didn&amp;#39;t know what to expect at Discovery but I walked away very impressed with the individuals in many aspects of Ontario&amp;#39;s entrepreneurship ecosystem, the growing synergy between government and startup sector, and the state of innovation in Ontario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am more convinced than ever that Ontario is one of the best places to build a startup. Innovation isn&amp;#39;t confined to &amp;quot;the valley&amp;quot;, it&amp;#39;s happening right here in KW, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fxTyS-aqdLE?t=8s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the 6&lt;/a&gt;, and all across Ontario.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 19:47:45 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/innovation-in-the-6/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/innovation-in-the-6/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>7 Personal Lessons from Founding a Startup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When people use analogies of your co-founder being like a wife, a startup as your baby, and employees as family, it shouldn&amp;#39;t be a surprise to find a startup has a massive effect on your personal life. I founded Teknically three months after I turned 18, so I already was growing at a fast pace becoming an independent adult. Being a founder put me in unique circumstances to force me to grow faster than I would have before. I am the man I am today because of Teknically, here are 7 personal lessons it helped me learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;0: Startup Laurier Chat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/9d5snONjSCk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I covered these 7 tips in a talk I did at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/startuplaurier&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Startup Laurier&lt;/a&gt; in January. Unfortunately the camera cut out midway through so I&amp;#39;ve tried to cover below the main points from the talk. Also here are the startup books &amp;amp; resources I mentioned in the talk:
- &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;The Essays&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; - Paul Graham
- &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0470929820/domofa-20&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Venture Deals&lt;/a&gt; - Brad Feld
- &lt;a href=&quot;http://zerotoonebook.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Zero to One&lt;/a&gt; - Peter Thiel
- &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.ca/The-Startup-Owners-Manual-Step-By-Step/dp/0984999302&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Startup Owner&amp;#39;s Manual&lt;/a&gt; - Steve Blank &amp;amp; Bob Dorf (Methodology taught at &lt;a href=&quot;http://laurierentrepreneur.ca/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Laurier Launchpad&lt;/a&gt;)
- &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; - Good beginner programming lessons
- &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeschool.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Code School&lt;/a&gt; - Very robust beginner to advanced lessons in almost any language/framework&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1: Two Things About People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parts &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-dream-fades/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; I give more details about our journey. In short, over 13 months we met hundreds of mentors, student entrepreneurs, experienced founders, and investors. I&amp;#39;m thankful to so many for their support and wisdom that helped us avoid many of the most common mistakes made as founders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, I also learned two key things about people that I have hinted at in previous posts and talks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;i) Everybody is just human.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no startup superhero founders. Stop worshiping people, it skews self thought about your own capabilities. Success isn&amp;#39;t limited to those with some supernatural ability, it comes down to hard work, perseverance, and a bit of luck. You can do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;ii) People don&#39;t know what they&#39;re talking about. &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few people are real experts, even fewer know your business better than you do. We came to realize that even though the mentors and entrepreneurs we met with were clearly intelligent people, nobody had the right answer all the time and some never did. The key was to listen, process, and confidently make decisions whether they aligned with all or none the perspectives we heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Embrace Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2007 I attended a National Speakers Association conference in San Diego and one of the self-made speakers shared a remarkable quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The average American reads 1 book per year. 
The average millionaire reads 1 book per week.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has always stuck with me and I&amp;#39;ve seen the consequences play out repeatedly when I forget to feed my mind. Read anything, read everything. Over the course of 2014 I averaged one book per month. Since January 2015, I&amp;#39;m up to one book every two weeks, still aiming towards the goal of one book per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve found the books I&amp;#39;ve read in the past 16 months have kept my mind alert, open to new ideas, and helped me grow as a person (wondering what those books were...find out in an upcoming blog post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with interesting biographies and relevant startup books. I soon branched into non-fiction, history, and even fiction (which I used to rarely read). Start reading with whatever you&amp;#39;re comfortable with and expand after that. Once you make reading fun, learning will be too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. 360º Leadership&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In high school I read a book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chapters.indigo.ca/en-ca/books/product/9780310495956-item.html?mkwid=8t6Z3MTe_dc&amp;pcrid=44154474422&amp;s_campaign=goo-Shopping_Books&amp;gclid=Cj0KEQjwl_6oBRDHxNGz6ueJufMBEiQAvm_k_kfLIX93EQO_JNhMc_Wf3Ohg75gStBv7SSBe4pNeJQQaAiva8P8HAQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Courageous Leadership&lt;/a&gt; by Bill Hybels  that fundamentally changed how I viewed leadership. He successfully proved that business management techniques were just as useful to build a successful church as they were in any organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He suggests in his book that leadership isn&amp;#39;t simple like a straight line. It&amp;#39;s not just leading those below you by setting goals or casting vision; as a team leader, 
club president, or even startup founder. True leadership extends for 360º.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-02-7-personal-lessons-from-founding-a-startup/360Leader.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of the 360º Leader (attr: ajoconnor.com).&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It involves leading by example and helpful words nudging in the right direction those beside you; as peers, classmates, or good friends. Leadership includes proving by example a better work ethic, a better way to live, addressing those above you respectfully; your bosses, executives, or elders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really resonated with me though was the revelation that none of these three areas is the most difficult to lead. The most difficult task is leading yourself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s the area where most leaders fall off the path, when they let themselves off the hook, don&amp;#39;t hold themselves to a higher standard, or don&amp;#39;t take the time and energy to keep improving themselves. It can be easy to settle into a complacency and prideful self-righteousness when you don&amp;#39;t lead yourself with the same vigor that you lead others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I have failed, it has almost always been as a result of a failure to lead myself. This failure is unforgiving and like a toxic oil spill, the effects eventually spread to all other areas of your leadership circle and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to be serious about becoming a great leader, be serious about leading yourself now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Dealing with Failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two distinct memories of becoming overwhelmed by failure in the course of our startup. Both revealed an immovable reliance I had put on success to justify my understanding of who I was as a person. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;i) Laurier Entrepreneurship Competition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-02-7-personal-lessons-from-founding-a-startup/LEC-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2014 we competed in the Laurier Entrepreneurship Competition and blew away the crowd with a very polished presentation. Compared to others who presented in terms of their idea and presentation I was sure without much of any doubt that we would win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s the assumption that makes you feel that third place was a failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was shocked and kept desperately wanting to know what did we do wrong? How could we have presented better? Which aspects of our product and business plan weren&amp;#39;t made clear? My parents and others helped me realize that we didn&amp;#39;t do anything wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life isn&amp;#39;t fair. Judges don&amp;#39;t always pick who should have won. 
The best don&amp;#39;t always win. Just accept it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took a while but I have. When we competed later in Halifax and Provo, my mindset going in was very different. I didn&amp;#39;t have any assumption that we would win simply based on being the best, we needed to tailor to the judges. In Halifax we successfully did that and won first place. In Provo, we weren&amp;#39;t as successful. Regardless of the results I was still very happy with how we did, separate from our place in the standings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;ii) Y Combinator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-02-7-personal-lessons-from-founding-a-startup/SFstation-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2014, we interviewed unsuccessfully at Y Combinator in Mountain View, California. My reaction then was different. I began to think back over everything we had accomplished; competitions won, mentors impressed, co-op students hired, innovative software designs, overflowing waitlists of customers. Had it all been false positives, had it all been for nothing? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I was letting the final result determine the binary judgement of the journey. If we had succeeded, the journey was a success; if we had failed, the journey was a failure. I was shortchanging myself by trying to reduce the complexity of our startup journey to a binary result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had succeeded in so many different ways. We had learned so much. No, we didn&amp;#39;t get into Y Combinator. And no, we wouldn&amp;#39;t be continuing the business. But by no means had we failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the greatest legacies of this failure will be not my complete rehabilitation, but the beginning of a new journey to root my self-worth in a foundation that doesn&amp;#39;t sway in the winds of failure or the rising tides of success.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Faith&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2015-04-02-7-personal-lessons-from-founding-a-startup/field-cross-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;#39;t be honest with you if I didn&amp;#39;t bring this up. Any founder will admit to the anxiety that can sink in late at night or right before an important presentation, the stress that can seem to compound with each day, the doubts of whether this is all going to be worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t think these feelings are necessarily limited to founders. In life all of us must deal with failures, stress, anxiety, fears, doubts, feelings of inadequacy. Some founders I&amp;#39;ve known have found relief in yoga, meditation, and regular exercise. Though I&amp;#39;ve also found relief in exercise and dance, I&amp;#39;ve only found one cure to these worries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My faith in Jesus Christ has been the rock on which I can stand through the storms of life. In Him I&amp;#39;ve been freed from the chains that held me when I based my self-worth in success and my own abilities. I no longer feel like an addict looking for the next hit of applause, success, or recognition. I no longer feel the need to maintain appearances of having it all put together. I don&amp;#39;t have a monopoly on the right way to live life, so I&amp;#39;m learning to better respect people from all walks of life. We&amp;#39;re each on our own journey, none of us are in a position to judge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I hope each of you finds a strong foundation to build your life upon. Christ is that rock for me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Yet a Better Way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spending first year at Laurier I&amp;#39;ve seen first hand what so many people do with their free time at this age. I don&amp;#39;t think it&amp;#39;s a stretch to say most of us don&amp;#39;t have kids, full time jobs, or mortgages. At this unique time in our lives don&amp;#39;t you think we might have a greater purpose than just partying?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As university students in the West, we already are among the top &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globalrichlist.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;0.5-4%&lt;/a&gt; of the world. We are equipped with resources and time that very few people in the world have. I don&amp;#39;t have any perfect answers on what we should be doing, but I feel we must do something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s easy to ignore the facts, to just stay busy with clubs, class, and parties. &lt;strong&gt;Most people don&amp;#39;t get the opportunity to live an easy life. The few of us that do, have the responsibility to not settle for it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Upcoming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! Please comment, subscribe below, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/andrew_paradi&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;follow&lt;/a&gt; if you&amp;#39;re feeling good vibes. Always looking for feedback! &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/innovation-in-the-6/&quot;&gt;Next post&lt;/a&gt; I go through 6 ways you can BBQ a squirrel...&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 14:04:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/7-personal-lessons-from-founding-a-startup/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/7-personal-lessons-from-founding-a-startup/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Five Lessons from Behind the Curtain</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When your world stops spinning, the lights fade, and the silence surrounds you, you can finally think. These past 13 weeks have been the beginning of my next chapter, the regaining of consciousness, &amp;amp; the recovery from 13 months founding a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This third instalment of the Teknically series transitions from telling our story to sharing the key lessons we learned. Part 3 examines what we learned professionally. Part 4 (coming next week), digs into how founding a startup poured gasoline on my personal development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pulling Back the Curtain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parts &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-dream-fades/&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; of this series, I&amp;#39;ve told how over 13 months we&amp;#39;ve been immersed in many aspects of the Kitchener-Waterloo Tech Scene. From Laurier Launchpad to winning national business competitions, Google for Entrepreneurs to managing co-op students and employees, pitching small business owners to interviewing at Y Combinator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ve been immersed in the &amp;quot;Startup Experience&amp;quot; like few our age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At our final Laurier Launchpad update presentation we summarized the five biggest lessons we had learned founding Teknically. Check out the video below, or skim the highlights in text. I hope it helps you see behind the curtain that makes startups seem unapproachable for most and only successful for the few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ilJwvC3H_lk?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Andrew and Brandon presenting the final Teknically update at Launchpad, filmed December 16, 2014.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. MVP: The Medium is More Important than the Message&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our original MVP (minimum viable product) was a paper custom report we called the Webplio Snapshot Report. We managed to sell a few of them in January 2014 to local small businesses who were very interested in learning more about their website. We thought this meant we had validated Webplio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We were dead wrong.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/jNR0WyG8Q9/?modal=true&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xpt1/t51.2885-15/e15/1599377_351877598287771_1712167658_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Right MVP, Wrong Medium: In the dead of winter, we sold 10 Webplio Snapshot Reports but it didn&amp;#39;t validate Webplio Dashboard. Medium matters.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it came to bringing these initial customers on board to Webplio Dashboard, few were interested. They liked the value of learning more about their website in the medium of a paper report they could hold in their hands. When we changed medium to an online dashboard, none of these initial customers were interested despite it being the same value proposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;#39;t assume you can change customer&amp;#39;s behavior.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had assumed that customers would love the information so much they would be willing to log on and see it on their screen. We were dead wrong in this assumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We realized the MVP must be the same medium as your final product. No alternatives (especially for software).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Speed to MVP is the most important goal. Period.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No business plans, wait lists, A/B testing of marketing, rockstar teams, competitions matter. Nothing matters until you have an MVP with users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We fell into this trap by thinking the Webplio Snapshot Report had validated our MVP requirement. We thought that since we had sold some of our MVP we were okay to move on with other important areas. Retrospectively, I think this was our biggest mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competitions ate up months of time early on that would have been better invested coding code and launching an MVP. If both of us had been coding, we would have reached this goal much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/lk6PPAG8eu/?modal=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xft1/t51.2885-15/e15/11373614_461456450692376_21313322_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;We were 1st place winners at CBMC in Halifax but lost focus of our main priority: releasing Webplio as an online MVP.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early development stage simply can&amp;#39;t be outsourced outside of the founding team. Somebody needs to know all the code from the beginning. As new members join, they can be the lead in bringing them up to speed and having them understand the vision of the product. This simply isn&amp;#39;t possible if coding in parts or whole is outsourced and contractors change every couple months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put simply, if you&amp;#39;re a business major who thinks your idea is the next Google/Facebook/Snapchat/Uber and all you need is a cheap coder or technical founder to be successful, you are delusional. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Execution is worth more than ideas. Learn to code so you can make your product vision a reality. There are no substitutes, no short cuts, and with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeschool.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Code School&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt;, and millions of other free resources there are no excuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;#39;re really serious about your idea, build it. If not, you&amp;#39;re still a wantrepreneur.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Do things that don&#39;t scale.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Webplio Snapshot Report we went straight into building the full Webplio Dashboard. We tried to jump from paper to perfectly scaled web app. What were we thinking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://paulgraham.com/ds.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Do things that don&amp;#39;t scale&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; is a classic piece of PG advice. 
We know now how profound it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should have focused on putting together a hack online MVP and launching as soon as possible. Instead of just entering data manually, we spent months perfecting the Google Analytics integration. Instead of launching with our first front end mockups, we went through numerous internal revisions until we were happy with it. Instead of launching with a basic signup page, we split test wait lists, copy, videos, and marketing techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, we had a product too big it was riddled with bugs, too long separated from actual users it wasn&amp;#39;t what they wanted, and a wait list of small businesses and organizations who never got to experience Webplio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Launch your MVP ASAP. Work with users to fix bugs, rework designs, and prioritize features. Scalability should be part of your product vision, but top priority is on getting an MVP to users.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Be your customer, use your competitors.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had never used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kissmetrics.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kissmetrics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://moz.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mixpanel.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mixpanel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crazyegg.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CrazyEgg&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://taplytics.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Taplytics&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://optimizely.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Optimizely&lt;/a&gt; and only primitively used Google Analytics. When we finally did give Optimizely and Mixpanel a try in October 2014 we realized that many problems in analytics had already been solved, and solved really well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The classic YC startup has founders who found a problem while doing their job, decided to solve it with software, reached out to peers and others who had the problem, and boom...scaled to a $100 million dollar company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to that story though is that it was the founders&amp;#39; problem to begin with. They had tried every possible solution. They had built their own hacks. They had lost hours of productivity and hours of sleep to the stress of this problem. They knew the problem best, so they could now solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our customer interviews, we knew that no small business owner we had talked to had even heard of any competitors to Google Analytics let alone used them. Thus we concluded that we didn&amp;#39;t need to try them either, we would just focus on Google Analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had assumed the only power of competing products was just that they had more accurate or real time data. It wasn&amp;#39;t until I started using Optimizely and Mixpanel that I understood just how difficult it would be to build a transformative product on Google Analytics data. We would have no ability in Webplio to show small business owners the data they wanted on call to actions, sales funnels, internal clicks, heat maps, and split testing results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is very possible to be successful by solving someone else&amp;#39;s problem. Your success becomes very unlikely if you don&amp;#39;t take the time to use competing products and understand how your product will be measured against incumbents.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. No founder is a superhero&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had opportunities to meet countless founders of startups in Kitchener-Waterloo, from around the world at the Kairos Global Summit, and even Y Combinator legends President Sam Altman, and founders Jessica Livingston &amp;amp; Trevor Blackwell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/110836607&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Highlight video for Kairos Global Summit, October 2014.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s easy to get sucked into believing the hype... the energy... the disruption... that everybody but you is successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting these founders and YC legends in person confirmed something I should have believed inherently: they are not superheros. Everyone no matter how successful is still human. It&amp;#39;s easy to point to Elon Musk, Thomas Edison, and Albert Einstein and say that some people are simply made for greatness. It is true no one could by hard work alone become a Musk, Edison, or Einstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the vast majority of other successful people, most have a base level of intelligence, innovation, leadership ability but the key differentiator is hard work and luck. There&amp;#39;s no formula for success, but it certainly isn&amp;#39;t limited to superheros, gods, or existing startup founders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We can all achieve greatness because even theirs is still only that which is possible for man.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;In Closing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/_DnKNClu2XM?t=1m45s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;no ragrets&lt;/a&gt;. I wouldn&amp;#39;t change any aspect of our journey, all the lessons I learned will be valuable for the path forward. I see life more clearly and am thankful for the journey and people that have led me here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m still learning so I hope you don&amp;#39;t take the above as fact. Take these thoughts, wrestle with them, and determine what you want to believe. Don&amp;#39;t take anything you&amp;#39;re told for granted. Make your own thoughts. Craft your own destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next post goes into how founding Teknically poured gasoline on my personal development, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/7-personal-lessons-from-founding-a-startup/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;check it out here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 12:09:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/lessons-from-behind-the-curtain/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/lessons-from-behind-the-curtain/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teknically Part 2: The Dream Fades</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Two eggs over easy, hash browns, double bacon, ham, sausage, french toast. It&amp;#39;s hard to tell which was the final straw but by the end of lunch on December 2nd, Teknically was finished. We were going back to university. Our startup journey had reached the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well I suppose this deserves a bit more explanation. Let&amp;#39;s go back to where we last left off: &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/&quot;&gt;...let the post-post-secondary adventure begin.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seemed to be the pattern with our startup journey so far, life without classes didn&amp;#39;t slow down, it only got faster. Within days of signing final deferral paperwork, we had decided to apply for Y Combinator and I already had plans to go to California!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-12-24-the-dream-fades/AndrewRitz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Andrew at the Kairos Global Summit, Ritz-Carlton Laguna Beach October 2014.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Writing with a Dying Pen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a Y Combinator (YC) application is like trying to write with a dying pen, each letter has a price. As Brandon continued Webplio development at a frantic pace, I began writing our application for the Winter 2015 YC batch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first draft was good by my standards, even my usual family and friend &amp;quot;editors&amp;quot; had little to change. My perspective shifted when we talked to our first YC alumni. In Skype calls and Google Hangouts our application was picked apart. In the most helpful way, alumni had specific insights and, of course, the single most important piece of YC advice: be concise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The single most important piece of YC advice: be concise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each major rewrite I managed to cut text by another 25-40%. By our final rewrite, we were down to counting syllables instead of words. On October 10th we opened our Webplio signup list and got 56 signups from different subReddits. In true Teknically style, we submitted the application with under an hour left before it was due on October 14th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody talks about the value of being concise. Applying to YC forces that realization. The experience has shaped how I write and evaluate the clarity of a message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ritz On the Rocks, Hold the Crackers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kairos Global Summit was an annual invite only gathering of 300 of the brightest student entrepreneurs in the world. From over 50 countries and 100 top universities, Kairos entrepreneurs were tackling tough problems in health care, clean energy, education, and other fields. Two weeks before the summit, my friend and President of Kairos Canada, Desmond Choi messaged me asking if I wanted to attend the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very surprised and honoured to be invited to the summit. Not only was this a very cool personal opportunity but with such a broad representation of entrepreneurs, VCs, and mentors, it was a great networking opportunity for Teknically. I quickly purchased plane tickets and 2 days after we submitted our YC application, I was on a flight to Los Angeles!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-12-24-the-dream-fades/KGS-Mike-Desmond.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Communitech Mafia Goes to California: Mike Reid, Desmond Choi, and Andrew at Kairos Global Summit.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hard to believe my eyes. Our hotel room overlooked the ocean and the conference events were held at the Ritz-Carlton Laguna Beach down the road. I had never attended an event with such luxuries and sponsorship subsidized costs for all attendees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were very interesting panels with industry experts from around the world. There were coaching sessions for fundraising and pitches. There was even a showcase for the K50 top companies of the year with technical innovations across many industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/110836607&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Highlight video for Kairos Global Summit, October 2014.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At dinners and social events I met fellow young entrepreneurs from around the world. These people, though they had accomplished so much more than me, were just as approachable, friendly, and genuine as anybody else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successful entrepreneurs aren&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;gods&amp;quot;. We can all achieve greatness because even theirs is still only that which is possible for man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There wasn&amp;#39;t any inherent &amp;quot;super power&amp;quot; they possessed. They weren&amp;#39;t radically more intelligent or innovative. They had kept working hard and managed to take advantage of the opportunities that were presented to them. Successful entrepreneurs, whether the ones I met or Bill Gates, aren&amp;#39;t &amp;quot;gods&amp;quot;. We can all achieve greatness because even theirs is still only that which is possible for man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;From A to YC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned from Kairos emboldened to work harder towards our goals. Over the next two weeks we made great progress and continued to grow our waitlist as we patiently awaited the result of our YC application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October 28th came and it was difficult not to keep constantly checking our email. We recognized intellectually that our chances were very slim. Over 5,500 startups apply each batch, less than 7% even get an interview, and under 2% are accepted. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a better chance getting into Harvard University than  YC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally at 6:22pm the email arrived in my inbox. &amp;quot;Thank you for applying to Y Combinator. Your application looks promising and we&amp;#39;d like to meet you in person...&amp;quot; We got the interview! I called Brandon, my parents, and enjoyed a couple minutes of ecstatic celebration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were just over two weeks until the interview. With our new relationships, we set up mock interviews with YC alumni. The Velocity YC Interview prep session gave us broad perspective. With just days before our flight, we revamped our entire value proposition to make it easier to understand. Hours of practice, countless rewrites, plane tickets bought: we were ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Through the (Silicon) Valley of the Shadow of Death&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To San Francisco we flew and each minute got more exciting. From the airport we took the BART subway. From the BART we took the CalTrain. Classic train stations for all of the Silicon Valley towns from Redwood City to Menlo Park, Palo Alto to Mountain View. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was my childhood dreams coming true...I really like(d) trains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-12-24-the-dream-fades/train.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in Mountain View, we struck two vital aspects of valley life off the bucket list: we took an Uber to our Airbnb. A bit more practice and nap time and then we went exploring. We ended up at a nice local Italian restaurant right on the downtown Mountain View strip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m pretty impressed, Andrew. This is the type of restaurant I thought we&amp;#39;d go to tomorrow night to celebrate,&amp;quot; Brandon said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought by this time we already had a right to celebrate. We were in Silicon Valley interviewing at Y Combinator. Pretty awesome for a pair of 19 year olds straight outta the 905.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-12-24-the-dream-fades/YC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Y Combinator. 335 Pioneer Way, Mountain View, California.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our interview was at 11:45am on a Thursday. We had a very calm morning leading up to it. We stopped by a Turkish bakery in town for breakfast, Uber-ed to YC, and had an hour to just bask in the glow of the orange walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was exciting to finally be in the place we had dreamed of, the common thread between Dropbox, Airbnb, Thalmic Labs, Pebble, and most of the top startups from the past decade. This exhilaration was met with an equally powerful feeling of peace. Not from confidence in our preparation and in our abilities, but from my faith. I felt no anxiety or fear as words of scripture echoed through my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;Though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil.&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Psalm+23&amp;version=NIV&quot;&gt;Psalm 23&lt;/a&gt; (KJV)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-12-24-the-dream-fades/Duo-at-YC.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Andrew and Brandon interview at Y Combinator, November 2014.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We interviewed with Sam Altman (YC President), Jessica Livingston (Founder of YC), Trevor Blackwell (Founder of YC), Jon Levy (YC lawyer), and Elizabeth Iorns (part time YC partner). Even when speaking with one of the toughest interviewing panels in the valley, I realized I wasn&amp;#39;t stressed. They were still just people, not &amp;quot;gods&amp;quot; of the startup world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ten minute interview flew by. I was happy, we had done our best, but now we had an afternoon to kill. Judgement would be passed down that evening in the form of an email (rejection) or a phone call (acceptance). Brandon and I both had our own coping strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-12-24-the-dream-fades/YC-Coping-Methods.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Different Coping Methods: Andrew finds out what&amp;#39;s at the bottom of a Ben &amp;amp; Jerry&amp;#39;s. Brandon...why so serious?&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got caught up on some Hawaii Five-0 episodes and then took the CalTrain up to San Francisco where we&amp;#39;d be spending the night at our friend Mike&amp;#39;s apartment. I got my camera out and had some fun capturing some of the cityscape and soon were eating at a California Pizza Kitchen...in California. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-12-24-the-dream-fades/Streetcar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Classic streetcar on Market Street in San Francisco as we get the YC email.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were walking to the Canadians @ YC meetup we got the email. It felt like being hit by a truck but with less blood. I was intellectually prepared for the email but not emotionally. I took a few minutes to pray and collect my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept reading the email over again. They liked us as founders but didn&amp;#39;t like Webplio. They thought we&amp;#39;d make good founders of a company but that there were marketing executives who had significantly more domain expertise in analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rejection stung, but they were right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just took us another three weeks to come to this realization ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then headed to the meetup. There were free drinks to dull the emotions, a panel discussion, and I got to meet some of the YC alumi with whom I had only Skyped. All were very encouraging and supportive knowing themselves that few startups ever get the phone call for their first YC application. We headed back to Mike&amp;#39;s for the night and got a couple hours of sleep before our 4am wake up to fly home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Dream Fades&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of us took some time to try and figure out what we would do next given our limited financial runway. We could start coding ourselves and reduce outsourcing costs. We could start working on another idea. We could shut Teknically down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We settled on cutting costs and each coding, but with a new idea that we could get to market in three weeks and hopefully revenue by Christmas. In meer days I had picked up Angular.js and Brandon Node.js, Express, and MongoDB. Two weeks in we had made remarkable progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, both of us were starting to realize that the dream was fading. Over a hearty Mel&amp;#39;s Diner lunch on December 2nd, we came to the conclusion that it was the beginning of the end. After 13 months of running on fumes, we needed time to breath. It was too late for another Hail Mary pivot. We would close up shop and go back to university. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Next Chapter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our dreams for Teknically may not have been realized in the fullest, but the legacy will live on in memories, refined skills, and lessons learned. We may have fallen behind in our degrees, but we got a massive head start on life experience. That is priceless. And that is why I have &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/_DnKNClu2XM?t=1m45s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;no ragrets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m thankful to many. Family and friends for your support. Dad for your guidance and steady perspective. Laurier Launchpad, Steve Farlow, Sandeep De, Dave Inglis, Anne Forler for taking a chance on a pair of first years who thought they could make Google Analytics better. Communitech. Google for Entrepreneurs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YC Alumni: Patrick Hannigan (Ticket Labs), Gareth MacLeod (Tinker),  Aditya Bali (BufferBox), Devon Galloway (Vidyard), Jim Robeson (PiinPoint), Euwyn Poon (Opzi), Trevor Creech (Tinker), Ross Robinson (Tinker), Ian Roberts (Ticket Labs) for your patience, kindness, and time whether reviewing our application, conducting mock interviews, or talking shop over burgers and Stellas. Desmond Choi and Mike Reid, fellow entrepreneurs but most importantly, friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m excited to start math classes at University of Waterloo in January and hopefully continue there in Computing and Financial Management (CFM) or Computer Science (CS) starting in Fall 2015. Brandon will be continuing in the BBA/Computer Science double degree program at Wilfrid Laurier University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is a wild journey. I&amp;#39;ve felt like I was on top of the world or other times like it&amp;#39;s caving in. Through it all, my faith has been the foundation that lets me confidently move forward to meet whatever life throws at me. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the old dream fades, a new one comes into focus. Keep dreaming new dreams, eventually one will come true.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 08:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/the-dream-fades/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/the-dream-fades/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mediator Features</title>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;Mediator Formats and CSS features&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples for different formats and css features&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Header Formats&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Header1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Header2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Blockquotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consetetur sadipscing elitr, sed diam nonumy eirmod tempor invidunt ut labore et dolore magna aliquyam erat, sed diam voluptua. At vero eos et accusam et justo duo dolores et ea rebum. Stet clita kasd gubergren, no sea takimata sanctus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Lists&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;orderd lists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;two&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;three&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;unorderd lists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an &lt;a href=&quot;http://example.com/&quot; title=&quot;With a Title&quot;&gt;example link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;Combinations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consetetur sadipscing elitr, sed diam nonumy eirmod tempor invidunt ut labore et dolore magna aliquyam erat, sed diam voluptua. At vero eos et accusam et justo duo dolores et ea rebum. Stet clita kasd gubergren, no sea takimata sanctus&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banana&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plum&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 09:34:25 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/mediator/feature/mediator_features/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/mediator/feature/mediator_features/</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>mediator</category>
        
        <category>feature</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>FAQ: Why Does Andrew Salsa Dance?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In November 2013 I had never danced before. One year later I&amp;#39;m dancing in a choreographed performance for the club&amp;#39;s end of term party. Crack a Coca-Cola and I&amp;#39;ll tell you the story of how I became a &amp;quot;Salsero&amp;quot; (or you can just skip to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/RVdGBEsZFws&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Learn to Dance&amp;quot; was on my bucket list when I started at Wilfrid Laurier University in September 2013. After my business lab I would often walk through the concourse and see the big circle of students dancing to salsa music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I had a meeting.&amp;quot; &amp;quot;My assignment was due the next day.&amp;quot; For 10 weeks I put off going to a class. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11 weeks in, I had run out of excuses.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-11-23-faq-why-does-andrew-salsa-dance/salsa-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;La Prima&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most things in life, it is a lot easier to start with the basics. &lt;strong&gt;11 weeks in, that wasn&amp;#39;t an option.&lt;/strong&gt; After explaining to each dance partner that, &amp;quot;Sorry, this is my first class&amp;quot; I was determined to get better, and fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next class went a bit easier, everybody was still so friendly, but it was the last one! Each semester ended with an End of Term (EOT) party at the on campus night club, the Turret. Dancers of all abilities (and in my case: inabilities) attended for a night of social dancing punctuated by choreographed performances by some of the better dancers in the club. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students from all faculties, Laurier, University of Waterloo, and the community came together through dance. Salsa music appealed to my love of a kicking brass section. The guy:girl ratio was on point. &lt;strong&gt;In three words: I was hooked.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the winter I attended Level 1 and 2 classes simultaneously. In the summer I was asked to be a TA for Level 1 and ended up helping with both classes. It was a refreshing break from our long summer hours with Teknically at Communitech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made new friends from more faculties and backgrounds than I could imagine. We learned more complex moves than I thought I could ever pull off. Salsa was the fun that made the summer fly by. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-11-23-faq-why-does-andrew-salsa-dance/salsa-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;La Hermana&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I auditioned for the EOT performance team earlier this fall, I did it more of a test of my skills than anything. I had no idea if I&amp;#39;d get in when there were many more experienced dancers auditioning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow I made the cut! Over the past ten weeks I&amp;#39;ve possibly learned more than I had in the previous ten months. I guess my lead has even improved because dance partners don&amp;#39;t feel the need to back lead as much!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;853&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RVdGBEsZFws?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;#39;Charanga Cubana&amp;#39; - starring the Fall 2014 KW Salseros Performance Team (I&amp;#39;m furthest to the right). Filmed November 21, 2014.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;La Familia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along each step of the journey, the leaders, instructors, and TAs have been so friendly, encouraging, and fun to be around. More than my newfound dance skills, I&amp;#39;m so thankful for the new friends I&amp;#39;ve made through my first year of salsa dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It really takes a village to raise a dancer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-11-23-faq-why-does-andrew-salsa-dance/salsa-instagram-eot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s never too late to find your passion. Even if it&amp;#39;s not salsa dancing, find a supportive community and go for it! Then again, it may be salsa dancing and you just don&amp;#39;t know it yet...;) Salsa class returns in January, so check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/kwsalseros&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;KW Salseros&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tocinillo. Coca-Cola. &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/_DnKNClu2XM?t=1m45s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;No ragrets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 15:42:25 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/faq-why-does-andrew-salsa-dance/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/faq-why-does-andrew-salsa-dance/</guid>
        
        <category>life</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Teknically Part 1: The 389 Day Laurier BBA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today I declined my co-op offer. Last week, I deferred all my classes. My time as a full time BBA student at Wilfrid Laurier University is over after 389 days.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-10-03-the-389-day-laurier-bba/Decline-Co-op.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering, why would anybody throw their university degree away, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newrepublic.com/article/118747/ivy-league-schools-are-overrated-send-your-kids-elsewhere&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the best proven opportunity for long term success&lt;/a&gt;? Why would anybody reject the chance be in the co-op program and &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/oGxBx8RzzrM?t=49s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ease on down the yellow brick road&lt;/a&gt; to a great corporate job? &lt;strong&gt;How did your parents let you throw your life away?!?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I haven&amp;#39;t had a chance to explain personally to many of you my reasons for deferring classes for a year, this post will hopefully answer the above questions. First, let&amp;#39;s roll the clock back and give a bit of context to our journey so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A Brief History of Teknically&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-10-03-the-389-day-laurier-bba/cofounders-kids-v3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Teknically Co-Founders Brandon Chow and Andrew Paradi circa November 2001&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My co-founder Brandon Chow and I first met in grade one and were good friends through grade school. We ended up going to different high schools but both ended up starting our own businesses. With Andrew Paradi Enterprises, I did freelance video production and web design. In grade 10, Brandon founded Provision Host, a niche server company that grew so large that in August 2013 it was acquired by an American company looking to expand into Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/jBEWp3G8Vt/?modal=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xaf1/t51.2885-15/e15/1597850_202788776592325_1804959790_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our first experience at Communitech was during Startup Weekend KW. For 54 hours, teams worked on a startup idea and pitched at the end of the weekend. Communitech is Kitchener Waterloo&amp;#39;s top technology center with programs for startups of all stages. It&amp;#39;s located at the Lang Tannery which is also home to University of Waterloo&amp;#39;s Velocity Garage, the Laurier Launchpad, and Google head offices among others.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 4 years of little contact, we ran into each other during Clubs Day as first year Laurier students in September 2013. After an exhilarating Startup Weekend KW working together at Communitech, I was hooked on the local startup scene. Brandon came to me the following week with an idea he had been working on and asked I if I was interested in joining. I joined &lt;a href=&quot;http://teknically.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teknically&lt;/a&gt; as co-founder and we hit the ground building &lt;a href=&quot;http://webplio.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Webplio&lt;/a&gt;, an online dashboard for business owners to easily understand their website performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/jNR0WyG8Q9/?modal=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xpt1/t51.2885-15/e15/1599377_351877598287771_1712167658_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;In the dead of winter, we sold 10 Webplio Snapshot Reports at $99 each in -30˚C weather. That&amp;#39;s cold calling.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We soon had joined the Laurier Launchpad, sketched initial Webplio logos on used napkins, and interviewed over 200 potential customers in -30˚C blizzard conditions. In January 2014 we launched our first MVP (minimum viable product), the Webplio Snapshot Report. Instead of going straight to building the online Webplio dashboard, we used the report to test our hypothesis that businesses would pay for easy to understand website performance information. In the dead of winter we went out and sold 10 reports at $99 each. Within 21 days we had set a new (and still unbroken) Laurier Launchpad record for fastest concept to sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/lk6PPAG8eu/?modal=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xft1/t51.2885-15/e15/11373614_461456450692376_21313322_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;We were 1st place winners at CBMC in Halifax beating top MBA and PhD teams from around Canada for the $25,000 grand prize.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, we competed against top MBA and PhD startup teams from across Canada at Dalhousie University for the Canada Business Model Canvas competition. For our innovative use of the canvas to tell our startup story, we won 1st place and $25,000. In May, we competed at the International Business Model Competition at Brigham Young University in Provo, Utah. Against the best MBA and PhD startups from Harvard, Stanford, and other top international universities, we finished top 40 out of 2,500 competitors. Thanks to our strong performance at these competitions, we were featured in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/careers/business-education/saskatchewan-schools-reduce-roadblocks-for-aboriginal-business-students/article17597347/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Globe &amp;amp; Mail&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.techvibes.com/blog/canadas-business-model-competition-2014-03-17&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TechVibes&lt;/a&gt;, and other &lt;a href=&quot;http://teknically.com/press&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;publications&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://instagram.com/p/nhIoqXm8bl/?modal=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xtp1/t51.2885-15/e15/1516398_627368947351437_1539864691_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At the international level, we competed against top teams from Harvard, Stanford and other top international universities and finished top 40 out of 2,500 competitors.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May we also hired three brilliant University of Waterloo engineering co-op students to work on Webplio Dashboard development until August. Our collective hard work moved Webplio from an idea to a working product in just 4 months. With the help of a fellow Laurier BBA friend in Mississauga, we also grew our initial waitlist to 30 diverse small business owners ready to test and pay for Webplio when it launched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/rItLgzG8WR/?modal=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-prn/t51.2885-15/e15/10593532_599420783512835_837079455_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;One of our bi-weekly sushi nights with our three University of Waterloo engineering co-op employees.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Turning Point&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past 6 weeks, a lot at Teknically has changed. At the end of August we were accepted as one of five companies in Canada&amp;#39;s only &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.googleforentrepreneurs.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google for Entrepreneurs&lt;/a&gt; program based out of Communitech. We were thrilled with the new office space (complete with Google ping pong table and astroturf) and ability to directly contact Google employees with specific questions on different products or APIs we were using. We even got to pitch Webplio to Google employees and management in the Google Waterloo office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/sidapiG8Z8/?modal=true&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent-ord1-1.cdninstagram.com/hphotos-xap1/t51.2885-15/e15/10683863_787043318013713_2093999175_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brandon and Andrew pitch to Google employees and management for the kickoff of their Google for Entrepreneurs tenancy batch.&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aspects alone were a big deal for us. The past two weeks have expanded what opportunities we think are possible. We recently received $100,000 in Google Cloud Computing credits. We also connected with top executives of Google Canada who actively want to partner with us to bring Webplio to more business owners. Unrelated to Google, our application for the Ontario Center of Excellence SmartStart $35,000 grant was approved so we&amp;#39;ll have funds to allow for expansion this fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$100,000 in free servers? Google wanting to partner with us? $35,000 grant? We were at a fork in the trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To fully take advantage of the resources and partnership available as part of Google for Entrepreneurs, we would need to work &lt;strong&gt;quickly&lt;/strong&gt;. To effectively leverage our grant money to exponentially grow Teknically, we would need to stay &lt;strong&gt;focused&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We remembered what it was like to work full time in the summer... We were remarkably focused, productive and made amazing progress...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To truly manifest our vision for Webplio, there was no doubt we would need to work full time. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within 48 hours of coming to this final conclusion, we had deferred our program, dropped all of our classes, and were now working full time on Teknically. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-10-03-the-389-day-laurier-bba/cofounders-launchpad-desk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Full Time Entrepreneurs: Brandon and Andrew working on Webplio in the Laurier Launchpad space.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Success Thanks to Many&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though many entrepreneurship stories attribute all success to the individual&amp;#39;s hard work, there are always people and experiences that prepared them so they could take advantage of their opportunties and be successful. I am still thankful when I recall the family, friends, and mentors who helped me become who I am today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned servant leadership from my Grandpa after long summer days working with my hands on different projects. I learned attention to detail from my Mom, pushing me not to accept anything less than my best. From my sister, I&amp;#39;ve learned perseverance. From my Dad, a logical approach to decision making and how to push myself to be a better entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From St. Andrew&amp;#39;s Presbyterian Streetsville and Camp Mini-Yo-We, a strengthened and unwavering faith. From my high school math teacher Mr. Spencer, university level financial mathematics skills. From my high school English teacher Mr. Blake, deliberate mindfulness and the ability to write clearly and persuasively. From my Graydon and Laurier friends, the value of a community that pushes each other to be better. From Laurier Launchpad, how to systematically test your assumptions about your product, customers, and market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many family, friends, and mentors to name have unknowingly fostered these skills and helped along each step of my journey. Thankfully my parents, sister, and extended family both understand and fully support my decision to defer classes and focus full time on Teknically. To God and all of you, I am truly grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Path Ahead&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-09-30-launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/Webplio-Dashboard-v3-Referrals.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we are working full time, we can push Teknically to Mach 2. Next week, &lt;a href=&quot;http://webplio.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Webplio&lt;/a&gt; launches exclusively to our initial 30 customers. In the coming weeks, we&amp;#39;ll begin to open access to select people signed up on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://webplio.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Webplio&lt;/a&gt; Wait List. We&amp;#39;ve begun hiring 2-3 additional full time developers to help us bring some truly unbelievable features and functionality to &lt;a href=&quot;http://webplio.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Webplio&lt;/a&gt; in the coming months. We&amp;#39;re also very excited for the continued opportunities that will come from our tenancy in Google for Entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-10-03-the-389-day-laurier-bba/cofounders-ping-pong.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Teknically founders Brandon and Andrew in their new Google for Entrepreneurs space at Communitech.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;September 24th was our last day as full time Laurier students. Now as full time entrepreneurs, we can&amp;#39;t wait to see what will happen in this second year of &lt;a href=&quot;http://teknically.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Teknically&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/_DnKNClu2XM?t=1m45s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;No ragrets&lt;/a&gt;, let the post-post-secondary adventure begin.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it did...in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-dream-fades/&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 19:58:45 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/the-389-day-laurier-bba/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Launchpad Meets Hack the North: 3 Hypotheses We Tested While Hacking</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking for Hack the North Part 1? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrewparadi.com/2014/09/3-ways-hack-the-north-improved-our-startup/&quot;&gt;3 Ways Hack the North Improved our Startup&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the Laurier Launchpad since October 2013, we quickly learned the &amp;quot;Lean Startup&amp;quot; methodology developed by Steve Blank, a legendary Silicon Valley serial entrepreneur and Stanford professor.  Distilled to one sentence, it is making decisions in your startup, not based on your intuition, but based on what your real results are with your product, market, and customers. Customer interviews, minimum viable products (MVP), and split testing marketing material are just a few of the many techniques used to test initial assumptions about your market, customers, or product. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout our development of Webplio, we have been successful at practically applying this methodology to our business (we have won over $27,000 at national and international competitions for our use of the lean startup process and business model canvas: &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/OB7m2iMaiA0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IBMC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/EhbbMZyOLsc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CBMC&lt;/a&gt;). As Hack the North approached we saw the opportunity to test three new assumptions we had for our product, market, and customers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt;: we could more easily build a fluid, efficient web app by leveraging the &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/VFqbGbU8f8o&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;synergy&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mean.io/#!/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MEAN&lt;/a&gt; stack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market&lt;/strong&gt;: Our Webplio &amp;quot;Scores&amp;quot; are not limited to just website analytics but could be applied to a financial data and provide significant value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customers&lt;/strong&gt;: people respond better to a simple straight forward demo video (a la &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/7QmCUDHpNzE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Product&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://webplio.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Webplio&lt;/a&gt; presents business owners with easy to understand website performance information and insights. It&amp;#39;s currently coded in PHP using the Symfony2 framework but we haven&amp;#39;t had time yet to build in any asynchronous technologies like AJAX. These types of web technologies allow for no page reloads, all data would change fluidly and dynamically. Within any browser and on any device, Webplio would be as fluid, fun, and approachable as an iPad app. The only question we still had was how we should implement this powerful functionality (there are a lot of options!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-09-30-launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/bob-webplio-hero.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Webplio&amp;#39;s vivid graphs, summary scores, and algorithmically determined insights work together to help owners make sense of their website analytics data.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many different ways to implement this fluid user experience, we wanted to test our top pick within a real project. Instead of just reading spec sheets, we could see how it interacts with our existing development styles and team. Based on Brandon&amp;#39;s extensive research, we decided we would test the entire MEAN stack with our Hack the North team to get a better feel for the stack synergy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-09-30-launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/stock-slate-demo-retail-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stock Slate: a fluid, real-time stocks web application built on the powerful MEAN stack.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stock Slate confirmed our hypothesis. Using the MEAN stack as the backbone for our real-time stocks application, we could easily test the most important capabilities of the framework. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could it process lots of data in real-time? Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could it easily plug into different APIs to grab the data? Yup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was the end user experience as fluid as an iPad app? You bet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hack the North provided a perfect opportunity to test if the MEAN stack would be the best way to bring powerful fluid functionality to Webplio users. Over the coming months we&amp;#39;ll be bringing some of the best aspects of the MEAN stack to Webplio. We can&amp;#39;t wait for it to feel more like an iPad app, and less like just another online dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the primary value propositions for Webplio are Webplio Scores. For example, instead of using 5 different metrics to evaluate effectiveness, Webplio users only need their Webplio Score which summarizes overall performance into a single number. Webplio Scores have been used to evaluate effectiveness of referral traffic, landing pages, and even server performance but had never been used outside of website analytics&lt;strong&gt;...until Hack the North.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-09-30-launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/Webplio-Dashboard-v3-Referrals.png&quot; alt=&quot;In this table from the Webplio Dashboard, Webplio Scores simplify analysis of referral traffic. Instead of looking at up to 5 different metrics, users only need to look at a single Webplio Score to quickly understand where their best referral traffic is coming from.&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our primary test with Stock Slate was to see if our approach with scores would be applicable to different industries and data sets. We had to address both the technical feasibility of a score addressing close to 10 metrics and additionally ensure that it was a valuable tool for user, not just another number in a table. We worked late into the final hours of Hack the North refining both of these aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-09-30-launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/stock-slate-demo-retail-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;In Stock Slate, Investor Scores simplify stock analysis to a single score of a stock&amp;#39;s value. This example show&amp;#39;s Peter Lynch&amp;#39;s algorithm being applied to some top retail stocks. It&amp;#39;s easily clear that investing in Family Dollar Inc. would be a better choice than Sears Holdings Corp.*1&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we showed peers, judges, and sponsors they all had the same reaction: &lt;strong&gt;disbelief&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;You automated fundamental stock analysis?! That&amp;#39;s genius. I&amp;#39;d use this.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Wow! Warren Buffett likes my picks! This is so simple.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Stock Slate, investing was now approachable to a whole new segment of the population. You could now make informed decisions without being a wall street banker or having a financial mathematics degree! It was very rewarding to see our vision of Stock Slate manifested in just 36 hours. We also were able to confirm our initial hypothesis that Webplio Score algorithms could successfully be applied to new industries and data sets. &lt;strong&gt;Mission Accomplished.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Customers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our initial promotional videos for Webplio, we didn&amp;#39;t yet have a working dashboard that we could demo live, so we compensated. Moving graphics and 3D effects helped give the illusion of a working product but it didn&amp;#39;t resonate with our potential customers. For Stock Slate, we knew we would have a working demo so we could try a new approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at other successful videos from startups and found that the first Dropbox demo video was unbelievably successful. CEO Drew Houston recalled the impact of the video, “It drove hundreds of thousands of people to the website. Our beta waiting list went from 5,000 people to 75,000 people literally overnight. It totally blew us away.”*2  When we dissected Drew Houston&amp;#39;s initial Dropbox demo it&amp;#39;s clear that they nailed the basics. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scripted conversation, not a pitch. Video screencapture demo. Simple articulation of value prop. Easter eggs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;960&quot; height=&quot;540&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/7QmCUDHpNzE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Narrated by CEO Drew Houston, Dropbox&#39;s first demo video was posted Sept 15, 2008 and almost overnight boosted Dropbox&#39;s beta list from 5,000 to 75,000 users.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Stock Slate we focused on the basics. Identify the problem. Demo how somebody would regularly use it. Show the power of the unique value proposition. When you don&amp;#39;t know your product, market or customers well enough, these basic tasks can require unnecessary explanation. With a 100 second time limit from Hack the North, we were forced to quickly distill Stock Slate to it&amp;#39;s most basic value proposition and articulate that concisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;960&quot; height=&quot;540&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/juY4bwJXMVE?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;When we initially posted the Stock Slate video to YouTube, the view count quickly hit 301+. Google does this when it needs more time to verify views for highly viewed videos.&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stock Slate demo video was our first video to hit the magic 301+ on YouTube. Within 60 minutes of posting it on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/investing/comments/2h8ha7/created_this_in_36_hours_looking_for_feedback/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;/r/investing&lt;/a&gt; we already had 9 people comment asking where they can sign up and start using it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This was a video that resonated with people. This was a video that inspired action. This was a video that would drive sales.&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to this powerful confirmation of our final hypothesis, we will be releasing a new Webplio demo video next week that gets back to the basics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether you know the &amp;quot;Lean Startup&amp;quot; process or not, start believing that &lt;strong&gt;everything you do is a hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt;. If it goes well, great! Figure out how to keep doing it better. If not, change your next decision to readjust your heading based on what went wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a startup, &lt;strong&gt;test all possible aspects of your product, market, and customers&lt;/strong&gt;. You&amp;#39;ll never regret having more data at your fingertips when making decisions about a new product feature, expanding to a new market, or better targeting your advertising to a specific customer segment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities to test your hypotheses are everywhere!&lt;/strong&gt; Take off your blinders! A/B test your marketing. Incorporate usage statistics into your product. Interview more customers to get their honest long form opinion. If you want to succeed as a startup, you need to know your product, market, and customers better than anybody else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Footnotes&lt;/strong&gt;
- *1 - Stock Slate does not provide financial advice in any form but is simply a data analysis tool for providing real time fundamental analysis. All investment decisions should be considered independently and approved by a professional advisor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;*2 - Drew Houston quote via &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2011/10/19/dropbox-minimal-viable-product/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Tech Crunch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 08:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>3 Ways Hack the North Improved our Startup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From September 19th to the 21st, University of Waterloo&amp;#39;s Engineering 5 building was over run by a native species of the region: hackers...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hack the North at UW gave 1,000 top hackers the opportunity to build something awesome in just 36 hours. Sponsored by top tech companies (Apple, Microsoft, Google, Facebook, Bloomberg, Uber &lt;a href=&quot;http://hackthenorth.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;...&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ycombinator.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/a&gt;, and with opportunities to use the newest technologies from Oculus Rifts to Thalmic Lab&amp;#39;s Myo, Canada had never seen a hackathon like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As co-founder of Teknically and currently deep in Webplio development, it would seem counter intuitive to drop what we were doing to build something at Hack the North. When I began to realize the sheer scope of Hack the North back in August, I saw a unique opportunity for Teknically to grow in new ways as a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are the three biggest ways that Hack the North has helped our startup.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Fresh Air&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hack the North was a breath of fresh air for our team. Webplio, over the past 10 months, has been ever evolving as we worked with more customers to better understand their needs. Our hack, Stock Slate, had a narrower scope and was a smaller application. We could move from an idea to a working prototype in the weekend. As each hour went by, we hit different milestones and at times needed to pivot and cut down on iterations. We applied a lot of the principles we knew from working at startups. To us, this was the startup life condensed down to 36 hours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/juY4bwJXMVE?rel=0&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Stock Slate Demo: Built on the MEAN stack and leveraging Bloomberg Open API, Stock Slate provides real time stock investment insights&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a new idea, new people, and new technologies, we were free to build something awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we contemplated entering Hack the North we were a bit worried whether we&amp;#39;d find other hackers qualified in the stack we wanted to develop on. What were we thinking?! After some serendipitous posting on the Hack the North Facebook group we assembled our dream team with some of the most perfectly complementary skills imaginable:
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Yutong Luo: Backend who has worked at banks and with many APIs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Brandon Chow: Initial idea conception, design, front end&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Andrew Paradi: Finance lead and algorithms expert&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Jason Kurian: A MEAN ninja&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/tOuf1WG8dI/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-g.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xfp1/1742199_290274417829046_1818926910_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stock Slate Team: Yutong Luo, Brandon Chow, Andrew Paradi, Jason Kurian&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our shared interest in learning new technologies and matching skills, our team was just filled with &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/VFqbGbU8f8o&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;synergy&lt;/a&gt;. We also had the skills to tackle new technologies. From the MEAN stack to the Bloomberg Open API it was a lot of fun working with new technologies to build out Stock Slate as a fluid one page web app. We even ended up winning the Bloomberg API Prize for best use of their API (each of us will be get a &lt;a href=&quot;http://ardrone2.parrot.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Parrot AR Elite Drone&lt;/a&gt; in the mail soon)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Competition You Can See, Hear, and Smell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work out of the Google for Entrepreneurs space at Communitech and are surrounded by other startups and technology companies building grand visions of the future. The difference with Hack the North is that the visions are just that much grander! There&amp;#39;s no need to worry about commercialization strategies or business plans. There&amp;#39;s only the singular focus on whether your hack works and how awesome it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone at the event is there in good spirit to have a good time and show what awesome things they can build. This style of competition opens the floodgates to simply indescribably innovative hacks such as my personal favourites: &lt;a href=&quot;http://hackthenorth.challengepost.com/submissions/27029-open-pokemon&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Open Pokemon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hackthenorth.challengepost.com/submissions/27086-silicon-man&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Silicon Man&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;video src=&quot;http://videos-b-11.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xaf1/10713849_1509221115984991_1899933270_n.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; controls&gt;&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Silicon Man: Why pay for an Oculus Rift and a Thalmic Labs Myo when you could strap an iPhone to your face and create a custom glove interface?!&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m a strong believer that you become the people you surround yourself with. That&amp;#39;s why I didn&amp;#39;t want to leave Hack the North when it was done. We were surrounded by wickedly smart, hard working, friendly hackers from around the world not motivated by monetary gain (they didn&amp;#39;t announce the prizes before hand, everybody applied for the love of hacking). It was an amazing group to be part of and we certainly left inspired by each other to keep building awesome stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Personal Hacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hack the North didn&amp;#39;t just bring together awesome hackers, it also provided some amazing opportunities for personal development. Throughout the hackathon were technical seminars with experts covering everything from iOS and Android app development 101 to talks from Google, Microsoft, and Bloomberg on broad development strategy. There were so many sessions that if you went to all of them you would have had no time to hack!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to leave enough time for hacking so we decided to only go to the keynote presentations. After seeing both, we have even more respect for the organizers of Hack the North for putting together the best speakers and panels I&amp;#39;ve seen in years. Friday night kicked off with a riveting discussion between investor Jason Calacanis and billionaire UW alumnus, former Facebook employee, founder of S23P, Chamath Palihapitiya. The length of his name foretold how big his thoughts were on startups and their role in society. He certainly forced me to think even further outside the box than I was used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chamath Palihapitiya: the length of his name foretold how big his thoughts were on startups and their role on society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday afternoon&amp;#39;s headline act was Y Combinator&amp;#39;s new President Sam Altman. He was interviewed by University of Waterloo&amp;#39;s Dean of Engineering Dr. Pearl Sullivan but we found the panel discussion that followed much more applicable to startup life. Moderated by Sam, the panel consisted of UW&amp;#39;s most successful YCom alumni with founders and CEOs of Pebble, Thalmic Labs, Vidyard, and A Thinking Ape all sharing valuable insights on what it&amp;#39;s really like to build a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/tLJ1t1G8b6/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://photos-b.ak.instagram.com/hphotos-ak-xaf1/10693659_1466888876932369_1764327461_n.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;UW + YC: Sam Altman moderates a panel of alumni from both University of Waterloo and Y Combinator: Eric Migicovsky (Founder, Pebble), Eric Diep (Founder, A Thinking Ape), Wilkins Chung (A Thinking Ape), Michael Litt (CEO, Vidyard), Stephen Lake (CEO, Thalmic Labs)&quot;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both speakers and the panel confirmed both that Waterloo is an awesome place to build a startup, but there&amp;#39;s nothing that can come close to the access to capital and mentorship that you get in Silicon Valley. Even though all of the UW YCom founders have since moved their companies back to Waterloo (or Vancouver for A Thinking Ape), each founder talked about how they still spend time regularly in the valley to maintain their networks and receive corporate guidance. For our startup, these two talks pushed us to set more concrete goals of how we will somehow make our way to the valley in coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had no idea when we arrived at Hack the North that the weekend would improve our startup, but it did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We thrived on the fresh air of working with a new idea, new people, and new technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our fellow hackers pushed us to keep innovating past the limits of our imagination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chamath and the UW + YCom Alumni panel inspired us to dream bigger of who we could become in just a few short years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our team won the Bloomberg API Prize!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is the first in our Hack the North series. Continue your reading with Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrewparadi.com/blog/launchpad-meets-hack-north-3-hypotheses-tested-hacking/&quot;&gt;Launchpad Meets Hack the North: 3 Hypotheses We Tested While Hacking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/article_images/2014-09-23-3-ways-hack-the-north-improved-our-startup/HTN-press-c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Update May 2015: We&amp;#39;ve been featured on Hack the North&amp;#39;s Press &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;http://hackthenorth.com/press&amp;quot; target=_blank&amp;quot;&amp;gt;page&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;!&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 10:34:25 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/3-ways-hack-the-north-improved-our-startup/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://andrewparadi.github.io/blog/3-ways-hack-the-north-improved-our-startup/</guid>
        
        <category>startups</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
